PRISON PLANET

By Bob Tucker

To remain on Mars meant death from agonizing space-sickness, but Earth-surgery lay days of flight away. And there was only a surface rocket in which to escape—with a traitorous Ganymedian for its pilot.

“LISTEN, Rat!” Roberds said, “what I say goes around here. It doesn’t happen to be any of your business. I’m still in possession of my wits, and I know Peterson can’t handle that ship. Furthermore Gladney will be in it too, right along side of that sick girl in there! And Rat, get this: I’m going to pilot that ship. Understand? Consulate or no Consulate, job or no job, I’m wheeling that crate to Earth because this is an emergency. And the emergency happens to be bigger than my position, to me at any rate.” His tone dropped to a deadly softness. “Now will you kindly remove your stinking carcass from this office?”

Unheeding, Rat swung his eyes around in the gloom and discovered the woman, a nurse in uniform. He blinked at her and she returned the look, wavering. She bit her lip and determination flowed back. She met the stare of his boring, off-colored eyes. Rat grinned suddenly. Nurse Gray almost smiled back, stopped before the others could see it.

“Won’t go!” The Centaurian resumed his fight. “You not go, lose job, blacklisted. Never get another. Look at me. I know.” He retreated a precious step to escape a rolled up fist. “Little ship carry four nice. Rip out lockers and bunks. Swing hammocks. Put fuel in water tanks. Live on concentrates. Earth hospital fix bellyache afterwards, allright. I pilot ship. Yes?”

“No!” Roberds screamed.

Almost in answer, a moan issued from a small side room. The men in the office froze as Nurse Gray ran across the room. She disappeared through the narrow door.

“Peterson,” the field manager ordered, “come over here and help me throw this rat out.. He went for Rat. Peterson swung up out of his chair with balled fist. The outlander backed rapidly.

“No need, no need, no need!” he said quickly. “I go.” Still backing, he blindly kicked at the door and stepped into the night.

WHEN the door slammed shut Roberds locked it. Peterson slumped in the chair.

“Do you mean that, Chief? About taking the ship yourself?”

“True enough.” Roberds cast an anxious glance at the partly closed door, lowered his voice. “It’ll cost me my job, but that girl in there has to be taken to a hospital quickly! And it’s her luck to be landed on a planet that doesn’t boast even one! So it’s Earth... or she dies. I’d feel a lot better too if we could get Gladney to a hospital, I’m not too confident of that patching job.” He pulled a pipe from a jacket pocket. “So, might as well kill two birds with one stone... and that wasn’t meant to be funny!”

Peterson said nothing, sat watching the door.

“Rat has the right idea,” Roberds continued, “but I had already thought of it. About the bunks and lockers. Greaseball has been out there all night tearing them out. We just might be able to hop by dawn... and hell of a long, grinding hop it will be!”

The nurse came out of the door.

“How is she?” Roberds asked.

“Sleeping,” Gray whispered. “But sinking...”

“We can take off at dawn, I think.” He filled the pipe and didn’t look at her. “You’ll have to spend most of the trip in a hammock.”

“I can take it.” Suddenly she smiled, wanly. “I was with the Fleet. How long will it take?”

“Eight days, in that ship.”

Roberds lit his pipe, and carefully hid his emotions. He knew Peterson was harboring the same thoughts. Eight days in space, in a small ship meant for two, and built for planetary surface flights. Eight days in that untrustworthy crate, hurtling to save the lives of that girl and Gladney.

“Who was that... man? The one you put out?” Gray asked.

“We call him Rat,” Roberds said.

She didn’t ask why. She said: “Why couldn’t he pilot the ship, I mean? What is his record?”

Peterson opened his mouth.

“Shut up, Peterson!” the Chief snapped. “We don’t talk about his record around here, Miss Gray. It’s not a pretty thing to tell.”

“Stow it, Chief,” said Peterson. “Miss Gray is no pantywaist.” He turned to the nurse. “Ever hear of the Sansan massacre?”

Patti Gray paled. “Yes,” she whispered. “Was Rat in that?”

Roberds shook his head. “He didn’t take part in it. But Rat was attached to a very important office at the time, the outpost watch. And when Mad Barry Sansan and his gang of thugs swooped down on the Ganymedean colony, there was no warning. Our friend Rat was AWOL.

“As to who he is... well, just one of those freaks from up around Centauria somewhere. He’s been hanging around all the fields and dumps on Mars a long time, finally landed up here.”

“But,” protested Miss Gray, “I don’t understand? I always thought that leaving one’s post under such circumstances meant execution.”

The Chief Consul nodded. “It does, usually. But this was a freak case. It would take hours to explain. However, I’ll just sum it up in one word: politics. Politics, with which Rat had no connection saved him.”

The girl shook her head, more in sympathy than condemnation.

“Are you expecting the others in soon?” she asked. “It wouldn’t be right to leave Peterson.”

“They will be in, in a day or two. Peterson will beat it over to Base station for repairs, and to notify Earth we’re coming. He’ll be all right.”

Abruptly she stood up. “Goodnight gentlemen. Call me if I’m needed.” Roberds nodded acknowledgement. The door to the side room closed behind her. Peterson hauled his chair over to the desk. He sniffed the air.

“Damned rat!” he whispered harshly. “They ought to make a law forcing him to wear dark glasses!”

Roberds smiled wearily. “His eyes do get a man, don’t they?”

“I’d like to burn ’em out!” Peterson snarled.

RAT helped Greaseball fill the water tanks to capacity with fuel, checked the concentrated rations and grunted.

Greaseball looked over the interior and chuckled. “The boss said strip her, and strip her I did. All right, Rat, outside.” He followed the Centaurian out, and pulled the ladder away from the lip of the lock. The two walked across the strip of sandy soil to the office building. On tiptoes, Greaseball poked his head through the door panel. “All set.”

Roberds nodded at him. “Stick with it!” and jerked a thumb at Rat outside. Grease nodded understanding.

“Okay, Rat, you can go to bed now.” He dropped the ladder against the wall and sat on it. “Good night.” He watched Rat walk slowly away.

Swinging down the path towards his own rambling shack, Rat caught a sibilant whisper. Pausing, undecided, he heard it again.

“Here... can you see me?” A white clad arm waved in the gloom. Rat regarded the arm in the window. Another impatient gesture, and he stepped to the sill.

“Yes?”—in the softest of whispers. The voices of the men in droning conversation drifted in. “What you want?”

Nothing but silence for a few hanging seconds, and then: “Can you pilot that ship?” Her voice was shaky.

He didn’t answer, stared at her confused. He felt her fear as clearly as he detected it in her words.

“Well, can you?” she demanded.

“Damn yes!” he stated simply. “It now necessary?”

“Very! She is becoming worse. I’m afraid to wait until daylight. And... well, we want you to pilot it! She refuses to risk Mr. Roberds’ job. She favors you.”

Rat stepped back, astonished. “She?”

Nurse Gray moved from the window and Rat saw the second form in the room, a slight, quiet figure on a small cot. “My patient,” Nurse Gray explained. “She overheard our conversation awhile ago. Quick, please, can you?”

Rat looked at her and then at the girl on the cot. He vanished from the window. Almost immediately, he was back again.

“When?” he whispered.

“As soon as possible. Yes. Do you know...?” but he had gone again. Nurse Gray found herself addressing blackness. On the point of turning, she saw him back again.

“Blankets,” he instructed. “Wrap in blankets. Cold—hot too. Wrap good!” And he was gone again. Gray blinked away the illusion he disappeared upwards.

She ran over to the girl. “Judith, if you want to back down, now is the time. He’ll be back in a moment.”

“No!” Judith moaned. “No!” Gray smiled in the darkness and began wrapping the blankets around her. A light tapping at the window announced the return of Rat. The nurse pushed open the window wide, saw him out there with arms upstretched.

“Grit your teeth and hold on! Here we go.” She picked up the blanketed girl in both arms and walked to the window. Rat took the girl easily as she was swung out, the blackness hid them both. But he appeared again instantly.

“Better lock window,” he cautioned. “Stall, if Boss call. Back soon...” and he was gone.

To Nurse Gray the fifteen minute wait seemed like hours, impatient agonizing hours of tight-lipped anxiety.

FEET first, she swung through the window, clutching a small bag in her hands. She never touched ground. Rat whispered “Hold tight!” in her ear and the wind was abruptly yanked from her! The ground fell away in a dizzy rush, unseen but felt, in the night! Her feet scraped on some projection, and she felt herself being lifted still higher. Wind returned to her throat, and she breathed again.

“I'm sorry,” she managed to get out, gaspingly. “I wasn’t expecting that. I had forgotten you—”

“—had wings,” he finished and chuckled. “So likewise Greaseball.” The pale office lights dropped away as they sped over the field. On the far horizon, a tinge of dawn crept along the uneven terrain.

“Oh, the bag!” she gasped. “I’ve dropped it.”

He chuckled again. “Have got. You scare, I catch.”

She didn’t see the ship because of the wind in her eyes, but without warning she plummeted down and her feet jarred on the lip of the lock. “Inside. No noise, no light. Easy.” But in spite of his warning she tripped in the darkness. He helped her from the floor and guided her to the hammocks.

“Judith?” she asked.

“Here. Beside you, trussed up so tight I can hardly breathe.”

“No talk!” Rat insisted. “Much hush-hush needed. Other girl shipshape. You make likewise.” Forcibly he shoved her into a hammock. “Wrap up tight. Straps tight. When we go, we go fast. Bang!” And he left her.

“Hey! Where are you going now?”

“To get Gladney. He sick too. Hush hush!” His voice floated back.

“Where has he gone?” Judith called.

“Back for another man. Remember the two miners who found us when we crashed? The burly one fell off a rock-bank as they were bringing us in. Stove in his ribs pretty badly. The other has a broken arm... happened once while you were out. They wouldn’t let me say anything for fear of worrying you.”

THE girl did not answer then and a hushed expectancy fell over the ship. Somewhere aft a small motor was running. Wind whistled past the open lock.

“I’ve caused plenty of trouble haven’t I?” she asked aloud, finally. “This was certainly a fool stunt, and I’m guilty of a lot of fool stunts! I just didn’t realize until now the why of that law.”

“Don’t talk so much,” the nurse admonished. “A lot of people have found out the why of that law the hard way, just as you are doing, and lived to remember it. Until hospitals are built on this forlorn world, humans like you who haven’t been properly conditioned will have to stay right at home.”

“How about these men that live and work here?”

“They never get here until they’ve been through the mill first. Adenoids, appendix’, all the extra parts they can get along without.”

“Well,” Judith said. “I’ve certainly learned my lesson!”

Gray didn’t answer, but from out of the darkness surrounding her came a sound remarkably resembling a snort.

“Gray?” Judith asked fearfully.

“Yes?”

“Hasn’t the pilot been gone an awfully long time?”

Rat himself provided the answer by alighting at the lip with a jar that shook the ship. He was breathing heavily and lugging something in his arms. The burden groaned.

“Gladney!” Nurse Gray exclaimed.

“I got.” Rat confirmed. “Yes, Gladney. Damn heavy, Gladney.”

“But how?” she demanded. “What of Roberds and Peterson?”

“Trick,” he sniggered. “I burn down my shack. Boss run out. I run in. Very simple.” He packed Gladney into the remaining hammock and snapped buckles.

“And Peterson?” she prompted.

“Oh yes. Peterson. So sorry about Peterson. Had to fan him.”

“Fan him? I don’t understand.”

“Fan. With chair. Everything all right. I apologized.” Rat finished up and was walking back to the lock. They heard a slight rustling of wings as he padded away.

He was back instantly, duplicating his feat of a short time ago. Cursing shouts were slung on the night air, and the deadly spang of bullets bounced on the hull! Some entered the lock. The Cen-taurian snapped it shut. Chunks of lead continued to pound the ship. Rat leaped for the pilot’s chair, heavily, a wing drooping.

“You’ve been hurt!” Gray cried. A small panel light outlined his features. She tried to struggle up.

“Lie still! We go. Boss get wise.” With lightning fingers he flicked several switches on the panel, turned to her. “Hold belly. Zoom!”

Gray folded her hands across her stomach and closed her eyes.

Rat unlocked the master level and shoved!

“WHEW!” Nurse Gray came back to throbbing awareness, the all too familiar feeling of a misplaced stomach attempting to force its crowded way into her boots plaguing her. Rockets roared in the rear. She loosened a few straps and twisted over. Judith was still out, her face tensed in pain. Gray bit her lip and twisted the other way. The Centaurian was grinning at her.

“Do you always leave in a hurry?” she demanded, and instantly wished she hadn’t said it. He gave no outward sign.

“Long-time sleep,” he announced. “Four, five hours maybe.” The chest strap was lying loose at his side.

“That long!” she was incredulous. “I’m never out more than three hours!” Unloosening more straps, she sat up, glanced at the control panel.

“Not taking time,” he stated simply and pointed to a dial. Gray shook her head and looked at the others.

“That isn’t doing either of them any good!”

Rat nodded unhappily. “What’s her matter—?” pointing.

“Appendix. Something about this atmosphere sends it haywire. The thing itself isn’t diseased, but it starts manufacturing poison. Patient dies in a week unless it is taken out.”

“Don’t know it,” he said briefly.

“Do you mean to say you don’t have an appendix?” she demanded.

Rat folded his arms and considered this. “Don’t know. Maybe yes, maybe no. Where’s it hurt?”

Gray pointed out the location. The Centaurian considered this further and drifted into long contemplation. Watching him, Gray remembered his eyes that night... only last night... in the office. Peterson had refused to meet them. After awhile Rat came out of it.

“No,” he waved. “No appendix. Never nowhere appendix.”

“Then Mother Nature has finally woke up!” she exclaimed. “But why do Cen-taurians rate it exclusively?”

Rat ignored this and asked one of her. “What you and her doing up there?” He pointed back and up, to where Mars obliterated the stars.

“You might call it a pleasure jaunt. She’s only seventeen. We came over in a cruiser belonging to her father; it was rather large and easy to handle. But the cruise ended when she lost control of the ship because of an attack of space-appendicitis. The rest you know.”

“So you?”

“So I’m a combination nurse, governess, guard and what have you. Or will be until we get back. After this, I’ll probably be looking for work.” She shivered.

“Cold?” he inquired concernedly.

“On the contrary, I’m too warm.” She started to remove the blanket. Rat threw up a hand to stop her.

“Leave on! Hot out here.”

“But I’m too hot now. I want to take it off!”

“No. Leave on. Wool blanket. Keep in body heat, yes. Keep out cold, yes. Keep in, keep out, likewise. See?”

Gray stared at him. “I never thought of it that way before. Why of course! If it protects from one temperature, it will protect from another. Isn’t it silly of me not to know that?” Heat pressing on her face accented the fact.

“What is your name?” she asked. “Your real one I mean.”

He grinned. “Big. You couldn’t say it. Sound like Christmas and bottlenose together real fast. Just say Rat. Everybody does.” His eyes swept the panel and flashed back to her. “Your name Gray. Have a front name?”

“Patti.”

“Pretty, Patti.”

“No, just Patti. Say, what’s the matter with the cooling system?”

“Damn punk,” he said. “This crate for surface work. No space. Cooling system groan, damn punk. Won’t keep cool here.”

“And...” she followed up, “it will get warmer as we go out?”

Rat turned back to his board in a brown study and carefully ignored her. Gray grasped an inkling of what the coming week could bring.

“But how about water?” she demanded next. “Is there enough?”

He faced about. “For her—” nodding to Judith, “and him—” to Gladney, “yes. Sparingly. Four hours every time, maybe.” Back to Gray. “You, me... twice a day. Too bad.” His eyes drifted aft to the tank of water. She followed. “One tank water. All the rest fuel. Too bad, too bad. We get thirsty I think.”

THEY did get thirsty, soon. A damnable hot thirst accented by the knowledge that water was precious, a thirst increased by a dried-up-in-the-mouth sensation. Their first drink was strangely bitter; tragically disappointing. Patti Gray suddenly swung upright in the hammock and kicked her legs. She massaged her throat with a nervous hand, wiped damp hair from about her face.

“I have to have a drink.”

Rat stared at her without answer.

“I said, I have to have a drink!”

“Heard you.”

“Well...?”

“Well, nothing. Stall. Keep water longer.”

She swung a vicious boot and missed by inches. Rat grinned, and made his way aft, hand over hand. He treaded cautiously along the deck. “Do like this,” he called over his shoulder. “Gravity punk too. Back and under, gravity.” He waited until she joined him at the water tap.

They stood there glaring idiotically at each other.

She burst out laughing. “They even threw the drinking cups out!” Rat inched the handle grudgingly and she applied lips to the faucet.

“Faugh!” Gray sprang back, forgot herself and lost her balance, sat down on the deck and spat out the water. “It’s hot! It tastes like hell and it’s hot! It must be fuel!”

Rat applied his lips to the tap and sampled. Coming up with a mouthful he swished it around on his tongue like mouthwash. Abruptly he contrived a facial contortion between a grin and a grimace, and let some of the water trickle from the edges of his mouth. He swallowed and it cost him something.

“No. I mean yes, I think. Water, no doubt. Yes. Fuel out, water in. Swish-swush. Dammit, Greaseball forget to wash tank!”

“But what makes it so hot?” She worked her mouth to dry-rinse the taste of the fuel.

“Ship get hot. Water on sun side. H-m-m-m-m-m-m.”

“H-m-m-m-m-m-m-m what?”

“Flip-flop.” He could talk with his hands as well. “Hot side over like pancake.” Rat hobbled over to the board and sat down. An experimental flick on a lever produced nothing. Another flick, this time followed by a quivering jar. He contemplated the panel board while fastening his belt.

“H-m-m-m-m-m-m,” the lower lip protruded.

Gray protested. “Oh, stop humming and do something! That wa—” the word was queerly torn from her throat, and a scream magically filled the vacancy. Nurse Gray sat up and rubbed a painful spot that had suddenly appeared on her arm. She found her nose bleeding and another new, swelling bruise on the side of her head. Around her the place was empty. Bare.

No, not quite. A wispy something was hanging just out of sight in the corner of the eye; the water tap was now moulded upward, beads glistening on its handle. The wispy thing caught her attention again and she looked up.

Two people, tightly wrapped and bound in hammocks, were staring down at her, amazed, swinging on their stomachs. Craning further, she saw Rat. He was hanging upside down in the chair, grinning at her in reverse.

“Flip-flop,” he laconically explained.

“For cripes sakes, Jehosaphat!” Gladney groaned. “Turn me over on my back! Do something!” Gray stood on tiptoes and just could pivot the hammocks on their rope-axis.

“And now, please, just how do I get into mine?” she bit at Rat.

EXISTENCE dragged. Paradoxically, time dropped away like a cloak as the sense of individual hours and minutes vanished, and into its place crept a slow-torturing substitute. As the ship revolved, monotonously, first the ceiling and then the floor took on dullish, maddening aspects, eyes ached continuously from staring at them time and again without surcease. The steady, drumming rockets crashed into the mind and the walls shrieked malevolently on the eyeballs. Dull, throbbing sameness of the poorly filtered air, a growing taint in the nostrils. Damp warm skin, reeking blankets. The taste of fuel in the mouth for refreshment. Slowly mounting mental duress. And above all the drumming of the rockets.

Once, a sudden, frightening change of pitch in the rockets and a wild, sickening lurch. Meteor rain. Maddening, plunging swings to the far right and left, made without warning. A torn lip as a sudden lurch tears the faucet from her mouth. A shattered tooth.

“Sorry!” Rat whispered.

“Shut up and drive!” she cried.

“Patti...” Judith called out, in pain. Peace of mind followed peace of body into a forgotten limbo of lost things, a slyly climbing madness directed at one another. Waspish words uttered in pain, fatigue and temper. Fractiousness. A hot, confined, stale hell.. Sleep became a hollow mockery, as bad water and concentrated tablets brought on stomach pains to plague them. Consciousness punctured only by spasms of lethargy, shared to some extent by the invalids. Above all, crawling lassitude and incalescent tempers.

Rat watched the white, drawn face swing in the hammock beside him. And his hands never faltered on the controls.

Never a slackening of the terrific pace; abnormal speed, gruelling drive... drive... drive. Fear. Tantalizing fear made worse because Rat couldn’t understand. Smothered moaning that ate at his nerves. Grim-faced, sleep-wracked, belted to the chair, driving!

“How many days? How many days!” Gray begged of him thousands of times until the very repetition grated on her eardrums. “How many days?” His only answer was an inhuman snarl, and the cruel blazing of those inhuman eyes.

She fell face first to the floor. “I can’t keep it up!” she cried. The sound of her voice rolled along the hot steel deck. “I cant! I cant!”

A double handful of tepid water was thrown in her face. “Get up!” Rat stood over her, face twisted, his body hunched. “Get up!” She stared at him, dazed. He kicked her. “Get up!” The tepid water ran off her face and far away she heard Judith calling... She forced herself up. Rat was back in the chair.

GLADNEY unexpectedly exploded. He had been awake for a long time, watching Rat at the board. Wrenching loose a chest strap he attempted to sit up.

“Rat! Damn you Rat, listen to me! When’re you going to start braking, Rat?”

“I hear you.” He turned on Gladney with dulled eyes. “Lie down. You sick.”

“I’ll be damned if I’m going to lie here and let you drive us to Orion! We must be near the half-way line! When are you going to start braking?”

“Not brake,” Rat answered sullenly. “No, not brake.”

“Not brake?” Gladney screamed and sat bolt upright. Nurse Gray jumped for him. “Are you crazy, you skinny rat?” Gray secured a hold on his shoulders and forced him down. “You gotta brake! Don’t you understand that? You have to, you vacuum-skull!” Gray was pleading with him to shut-up like a good fellow. He appealed to her. “He’s gotta brake! Make him!”

“He has a good point there, Rat,” she spoke up. “What about this half-way line?”

He turned to her with a weary ghost of the old smile on his face. “We passed line. Three days ago, maybe.” A shrug of shoulders.

“Passed!” Gray and Gladney exclaimed in unison.

“You catch on quick,” Rat nodded. “This six day, don’t you know?”

Gladney sank back, exhausted. The nurse crept over to the pilot. “Getting your figures mixed, aren’t you?”

Rat shook his head and said nothing.

“But Roberds said eight days, and he—”

“—he on Mars. I here. Boss nuts, too sad. He drive, it be eight days. Now only six.” He cast a glance at Judith and found her eyes closed. “Six days, no brake. No.”

“I see your point, and appreciate it,” Gray cut in. “But now what? This deceleration business... there is a whole lot-1 don’t know, but some things I do!”

Rat refused the expected answer. “Land tonight, I think. Never been to Earth before. Somebody meet us, I think.”

“You can bet your leather boots somebody will meet us!” Gladney cried. Gray turned to him. “The Chief’ll have the whole planet waiting for you!” He laughed with real satisfaction. “Oh yes, Rat, they’ll be somebody waiting for us all right.” And then he added: “If we land.”

“Oh, we land.” Rat confided, glad to share a secret.

“Yeah,” Gladney grated. “But in how many little pieces?”

“I’ve never been to Earth before. Nice, I think.” Patti Gray caught something new in the tone and stared at him. Gladney must have noticed it, too.

The Centaurian moved sideways and pointed. Gray placed her eyes in the vacated position.

“Earth!” she shouted.

“Quite. Nice. Do me a favor?”

“Just name it!”

“Not drink long time. Some water?”

Gray nodded and went to the faucet. The drumming seemed remote, the tension vanished. She was an uncommonly long time in returning, at last she appeared beside him, outstretched hands dry.

“There isn’t any left, Rat.”

Rat batted his tired eyes expressively. “Tasted punk,” he grinned at her.

She sat down on the floor suddenly and buried her face.

“Rat,” she said presently, “I want to ask you something, rather personal? Your... name. ‘Rat’? Roberds told me something about your record. But... please tell me, Rat. You didn’t know the attack was coming, did you?”

He grinned again and waggled his head at her. “No. Who tell Rat?” Suddenly he was deadly serious as he spoke to her. “Rat a.w.o.l., go out to help sick man alone in desert. Rat leave post. Not time send call through. Come back with man, find horrible thing happen.”

“But why didn’t you explain?”

He grinned again. “Who believe? Sick man die soon after.”

Gladney sat up. He had heard the conversation between the two. “You’re right, Rat. No one would have believed you then, and no one will now. You’ve been safe enough on Mars, but the police will nab you as soon as you get out of the ship.”

“They can’t!” cried Patti Gray. “They can’t hurt him after what he’s done now.”

The Centaurian grinned in a cynical way.

“Police not get me, Gladney. Gladney’s memory damn punk, I think. Earth pretty nice place, maybe. But not for Rat.”

Gladney stared at him for minutes. Then: “Say, I get it... you’re—”

“Shut up!” Rat cut him off sharply. “You talk too much.” He cast a glance at Nurse Gray and then threw a meaning look at Gladney.

GLADNEY subsided. Patti Gray noted with dawning wonder that his face had lost the loathing and anger he had previously held toward the outlaw pilot.

“Look, Sea!” Rat said a few moments later. Gray was in her hammock. She twisted over as he moved bony shoulders aside to let her see through the vision port. A startlingly brief glimpse of glistening waters shot past, reflecting a dancing moonpath. A continent whirled into place on the plate. The skies were clear of other craft.

“Travelling fast!” she warned. “I hope you know what you’re doing.” Another body of water shot past them beneath. “That must be the Pacific. Where are you going to set down?”

“The ocean.” Rat didn’t turn his attention away from the plate. “Gladney you got bad memory too much. That’s why we passed half-way line full speed 1 Sea water good brake, stop us hundred miles!”

Gladney flopped back. “May I be kicked to death! Of course! I’ve heard of it being done by stunt pilots. But Rat, are you sure you can do it? I mean, can you land us without killing us all?”

“Oh yes,” but Rat was grimly serious. “I can all right, but...”

“... but what?”

“Ever see little boy skipping stones across water?” His hand shot out and described a series of violent ricocheting motions. “Like that? We land that way, I think. Splat-splat! First splat knock us all... all... what you say?”

“Knock us out?” Gladney supplied.

Rat shrugged. Gray caught his eyes.

“Goodnight, Rat,” she smiled at him. “When I wake up, I want to see you again. You won’t be in jail for awhile, not until the hospital releases you, and perhaps by that time...”

“All no bother, please. I liked you Patti Gray. But your memory pretty punk too. Forget your Fleet training, I think. Yes! But Patti...” he stopped, helpless.

“Yes?”

“I’m sorry about something. I kicked you.”

“Rat, please forget it. I won’t forgive you for there is nothing to forgive you for!” She smiled at him, winked once and closed her eyes. “Goodnight everyone.”

They felt the nose dip as Rat dropped toward the moonlit sea. The ocean rushed up. The ship struck with titanic force, blasting through the white-caps, metal crumpling from the monstrous dive. And then all consciousness blacked out for those on board.

PATTI GRAY awoke, pressed the button under her pillow for a nurse, smiled about the clean hospital room.

Gladney was waiting to see her. He wheeled himself in and stopped the chair beside her bed.

“Hello. Feel human again?”

“Do I?” She laughed. “Gladney, I’m going to stay right here the rest of my life!”

“Yeah... that’s what I said yesterday. But today I’m itching to get back up yonder.” He dug a thumb at the sky.

“Is Judith all right?”

“Sure. She wants to see you. Frankly, Miss Gray,” he lowered his voice, “I expected that first ‘splat’ of Rat’s would kill her.”

Gray shivered. “I have a hazy memory of that landing. How did we do it?”

“Easy. A coast-guard cutter saw U9 and picked us up about ten miles out.”

“Gladney,” she said quickly, “you’ve got to help me clear Rat. We’ve got to... why Gladney, you don’t mean they got him...?”

“They didn’t get him. Earth did. Don’t you remember what he said about Earth being a nice place for us? Centaurians can’t endure Earth’s gravity and atmosphere; the Centaurian Embassy is very specially built, and all Centaurians come to Earth in what are virtually fish bowls.

“Rat was beginning to die even as we dove for the water.”

Patti Gray stared at him a moment in frozen horror, then buried her face in the pillow.

“Some day, he will be remembered, Miss Gray,” Gladney whispered. “Some day, after all the bitterness over Ganymede is forgotten, they’ll remember why Rat left his post, and they’ll remember how he drove.”

SPACE OASIS

By Raymond Z. Gallun

Space-weary rocketmen dreamed of an asteroid Earth. But power-mad Norman Haynes had other plans—and he spread his control lines in a doom-net for that oasis in space.

I FOUND Nick Mavrocordatus scanning the bulletin board at the Haynes Shipping Office on Enterprize Asteroid, when I came back with a load of ore from the meteor swarms.

He looked at me with that funny curve on his lips, that might have been called a smile, and said, “Hi, Chet,” as casually as though we’d seen each other within the last twenty-four hours.... “Queer laws they got in the Space Code, eh? The one that insists on the posting of casualty lists, for instance. You’d think the Haynes Company would like to keep such things dark,”

I didn’t say anything for a moment, as my eyes went down those narrow, typed columns on the bulletin board: Joe Tiffany—dead—space armor defect.... Hermann Schmidt and Lan Harool—missing—vicinity of Pallas.... Irvin Davidson—hospitalized—space blindness....

There was a score of names of men I didn’t know, in that space-blindness column. And beneath, there was a much longer line of common Earth-born and Martian John-Henrys, with the laconic tag added at the top—hospitalized—mental. Ditto marks saved the trouble of retyping the tag itself, after each name.

One name caught my eye.

Ted Bradley was listed there. Ted Bradley from St. Louis, my and Nick Mavrocordatus’ home town. It gave me a little jolt, and a momentary lump somewhere under my Adam’s Apple. I knew the state Bradley would be in. Not a man any more—no longer keen and sure of himself. A year out here among the asteroids had changed all that forever.

Shoving from one drifting, meteoric lump to another, in a tiny space boat. 30 Chipping at those huge, grey masses with a test hammer that makes no sound in the voidal vacuum. Crawling over jagged surfaces, looking for ores of radium and tantalum and carium—stuff fabulously costly enough to be worth collecting, for shipment back to the industries of Earth, at fabulous freight rates, on rocket craft whose pay-load is so small, and where every gram of mass is at premium.

No, Ted Bradley would never be himself again. Like so many others. It was an old story. The almost complete lack of gravity, out here among the asteroids, had disturbed his nerve-centers, while cosmic rays seeped through his leaded helmet, slowly damaging his brain.

There was more to it than the airlessness, and absence of weight, and the cosmic rays. There was the utter silence, and the steady stars, and the blackness between them, and the blackness of the shadows, like the fangs of devils in the blazing sunshine. All of this was harder than the soul of any living being.

And on top of all this, there was usually defeat and shattered hope. Not many futures were made among the asteroids by those who dug for their living. Prices of things brought from Earth in fragile, costly space craft were too high. Moments of freedom and company were too rare, and so, hard-won wealth ran like water.

Ted Bradley was gone from us. Call him a corpse, really. In the hospital here on Enterprize, he was either a raving maniac, or else—almost worse—he was like a little child, crooning over the wonder of his fingers.

It got me for a second. But then I shrugged. I’d been out here two years. An old timer. I knew how empires were built. I knew, better than most, how to get along out here. Be fatalistic and casual. Don’t worry. Don’t plan too much. That way I’d stayed right-side-up. I’d even had quite a lot of fun, being an adventurer, against that gigantic, awesome background of the void.

I didn’t consider my thoughts about Ted Bradley worth mentioning to Nick Mav-rocordatus. He was probably thinking about Ted, too, and that was enough.

“Come on, Nick,” I said. “They’ve got my ore weighed and analyzed for content in the hopper rooms. I’m going into the pay-office and get my dough. Then we might shove off to the Iridium Circle, or some other joint, and have us a time, huh?”

Nick laughed, then, good-naturedly, triumphantly. I gave him a sharp glance, noticing that under his faintly bitter air, there seemed to be something big. Some idea that gripped him, confused him, thrilled him. His small, knotty body was taut with it; his dark eyes, under the curly black hair that straggled down his forehead, glowed with a far-away look.

Of course, he was still very young—only twenty-two, which to me, at twenty-five, with a six-months edge of asteroid-lore beyond his year and a half of experience, made me feel old and disillusioned and practical, by comparison.

“All right, Chet,” he said at last. “Let’s get your money. Celebrations are in order—on me, though. But I guess we’d better soft-pedal them some. I’ve got a lot to tell you, and more to do.”

I didn’t give his words proper attention, just then. I swaggered into the pay office, where a couple of stenogs clicked typewriters, and where Norman Haynes, acting head of the Haynes Shipping Company, sat at his desk, under the painted portrait of his uncle, that grizzled old veteran, Art Haynes, who had retired years ago, and who now lived on Earth.

I knew old Art only by reputation. But that was enough to arouse my deep respect. Between nephew and uncle there was a difference as great as between night and day. The one, the founder, unafraid to dirty his hands and face death, and build for the future. Tough, yes, but square, and willing to pay bonuses to miners even while he’d been struggling to expand his company, and open up vast, new space trails. The other, an arm-chair director, holding on tight, now, to an asteroid empire, legally free of his control, but whose full resources came eventually into his hands at the expense of others, because he controlled the fragile, difficult supply lines.

At sight of me, Norman Haynes arose from his chair. He was very tall, and he wore an immaculate business suit. He was smooth-shaven, with a neat haircut, in contrast to my shaggy locks and bristles. Across his face spread a smile of greeting as broad as it was false.

“Well—Chet Wallacehe said. “You’ve done some marvelous meteor mining, this trip: Nineteen hundred dollars’ worth of radium-actinium ore! Splendid 1 Maybe you’ll do even better next time!”

YEAH! I’d seen and heard Norman Haynes act and talk like this before. He handed out the same line to all of the miners. To me it was forever irritating. Always I’d wanted to turn that long nose of his back against his right ear. He and his words were both phony. Always he used a condescending tone. And I felt that he was a bloodsucker. My anger was further increased, now, because of Ted Bradley.

I guess I sneered. “Don’t worry about those nineteen hundred dollars, Mr. Haynes,” I said. “When I buy grub, and a few things I need, and have a little blow, you’ll have the money all back.”

Beside the office railing there was a machine—a cigarette vendor. Into a roller system at its top, I inserted two five-dollar bills from my pay. There was a faint whir as the robot photographic apparatus checked the denominations of the notes, and proved their authenticity. Two packs of cigarettes slipped down into the receiver arrangement.

“Five bucks apiece, Haynes,” I said. “At a fair shipping rate, cigarettes brought out from Earth aren’t worth much more than three bucks. But you’re just a dirty chiseller, not satisfied with a fair profit. Costs here in the asteroids are naturally plenty steep; but you make a bad situation worse by charging at least twenty-five per-cent more than’s - reasonable! A Venutian stink-louse is more of a gentleman than you are, Haynes!”

Oh, there was a Satanic satisfaction in feeling the snarl in my throat, and seeing Haynes’ face go purplish red, and then white with surprise and fury. Some other space men had entered the pay office, and they hid their grins of pleasure behind calloused palms.

First I thought Normaii Haynes would swing at me. But he didn’t. He lacked that kind of nerve. He began to sputter and curse under his breath, and I thought of a snake hissing. I felt the danger of it, though—danger that broods and plans, and doesn’t come out into the open, but waits its chance to strike. Knowing that it was there, sizzling in Haynes’ mind, gave me a thrill.

Casually I tossed one of the packs of cigarettes to Nick Mavrocordatus, who had come with me into the pay office. He gave me a nudge, which meant we’d better scram. When we were out of the building, he held me off from going to any of the few tawdry saloons there under the small, glassed-in airdome of Enter-prize City, the one shabby scrap of civilization and excuse for comfort.

“No drinks now, Chet,” Nick whispered. “Can’t chance it. Got to keep on our toes. In one way I’m glad you talked down to that—whatever you want to call him. But you’ve made us the worst possible enemy we could have—now.”

I shrugged. “What were you gonna tell me before, Nick?” I demanded. “I gathered you had something plenty big in view.”

He answered me so abruptly that I didn’t quite believe my ears at first. “Pa and Sis and Geedeh and I, have made good, Chet,” he said. “We found—not just pickings—but a real fortune in ore, on planetoid 439. So rich is the deposit that we could buy our own smelting and purifying machinery, and hire ships under our own control, to take the refined metals back to Earth!”

“You’re kidding, Nick,” I said amazedly.

“Not a bit of it,” he returned.

THEN I was pumping his hand, congratulating him. Really good luck was a phenomenon among the asteroids. That friends of mine, among the thousands of hopeful ones that I didn’t know, should grab the jack-pot, seemed almost impossible.

“I suppose you’ll all be leaving us soon,” I told him. “Going back to Earth, living the lives of millionaires. I’m glad for you all, kid. Your Pa can raise his flowers and grapes, instead of starting up in the truck-garden business again. Your sis, Irene, can study her painting and her music, like she wants to.”

Anybody can see the way my thoughts were going just then. When you start out green for the Minor Planets, that’s part of what’s in your mind, first—get rich, come back to Earth.

Nick sighed heavily as we walked along. That funny smile was on his lips again. He glanced around, and the emerald light of the illuminators was on his young face.

Then he said, “I don’t think it’s quite safe to talk here, Chet. Better come to our old space jaloppy, the Corfu.”

The Corfu was on the ways outside the dome. We put on space suits to reach it. Inside, the old crate smelled of cooking odors, some of them maybe accumulated over the eighteen months the Mavrocordatuses had been asteroid mining. Old ships are hard to ventilate, with their imperfect air-purifiers.

The instruments in the control room, were battered and patched; and from the living quarters to the rear, issued a duet of snores—one throaty and rattly, Pa Mavrocordatus’ beyond doubt; and the other an intermittent hiss, originating unquestionably in the dust-filtering hairs in the larynx of Geedeh, the little Martian scientist, whom Nick had befriended.

“I can’t figure you out, Nick,” I said. “Rich, and not leaving this hell-hole of space. You’re an idiot.”

“So are you, Chet,” he returned knowingly. “In my place, you wouldn’t go either—at least not without regrets. In spite of all hell, there’s something big here in space that gets you. You feel like nothing, yourself. But you feel that you’re part of something terribly huge and terribly important. You’d be happy on Earth for a week; then you’d begin to smother inside. The Minor Planets have become our home. Chet. It’s too late to break the ties.”

Slowly it soaked into my mind that Nick was right.

“Not to say anything bad against old Mother Earth, Chet,” he continued. “Far from it! That’s just what’s needed out here—a little touch of our native scene. Growing things. A piece of blue sky, maybe. Enough gravity to make a man believe in solid ground again.

Right then I began to smell Nick’s plan, not only what it was, but all the impractical dreamer part of it.

I began to grin, but there was a kind of sadness in me, too. “Sure! Sure, Nick!” I chided. “The idea’s as old as the hills! Rejuvenate some asteroid. Bring in soil and water and air from Earth. Install a big gravity-generating unit. Ha! Have you any idea how many ships it would take to bring those thousands and thousands of tons of stuff out here—even to get started?”

I WAS talking loud. My voice was booming through the rusty hull of the Corfu, making ringing echoes. So just about as I finished, they were all around me. Pa Mavrocordatus, in pajamas and ragged dressing gown, his handle-bar moustaches bristling. Geedeh, the tiny Martian, draped in a checkered Earthly blanket, his great eyes blinking, and his tiny fingers, with fleshy knobs at their ends instead of nails, twiddling nervously near the center of his barrel-chest. And Irene, too, standing straight and defiant and little, in her blue smock.

Irene hadn’t been sleeping. Probably she’d been washing dishes, and straightening up the galley after supper. She still had a dish towel in her hands. Wealth hadn’t altered the Mavrocordatus’ mode of life, yet. Irene looked like a bold little kewpie, her dark head of tousled, curly hair, not up to my shoulder. She was exquisitely pretty; but now she was somewhat irritated.

She shook a finger up at me, angrily. “You think Nick has a dumb idea, eh, Chet Wallace?” she accused. “That’s only because you don’t know what you’re talking about! We won’t have to bring a drop of water, or a molecule of air or soil, out from Earth! You ask Geedeh!”

I turned toward the little Martian. The dark pupil-slits, and the yellow irises of his huge eyes, covered me. “Irene has spoke the truth, Chet,” he told me in his slow, labored English. “The Asteroid Belt, the many hundreds of fragments that compose it, are the remains of a planet that exploded. So there is soil on many of the asteroids. Dried out—yes—after most of the water and air disappeared into space, following the catastrophe. But the soil can still be useful. And there is still water, not in free, liquid form, but combined in ancient rock strata; gypsum, especially. It is like on Mars, when the atmosphere began to get too thin for us to breathe, and the water very scarce on the dusty deserts.

I said nothing, wished I had kept silent.

“We roasted gypsum in atomic furnaces,” Geedah finished, “driving the water out as steam, and reclaiming it for our underground cities. The same can be done here among the Minor Planets. And since water is hydrogen oxide, oxygen can be obtained from it, too, by electrolysis. Nitrogen and carbon dioxide, necessary to complete the new atmosphere, which will be prevented from leaking into space by the force of the artificial gravity, can be obtained from native nitrates, and other compounds. Only vital parts of the machinery need be brought out from Earth and Mars by rocket. The rest can be made here, from native materials.”

Geedeh’s voice, as he spoke to me, was a soft, sibilant whisper, like the rustle of red dust in a cold, thin, Martian wind.

“You bet ” Pa Mavrocordatus enthused.

“Nick’s got a good idea. I’m gonna raise my flowers! I’m gonna raise tomatoes and cabbages and carrots, right here on one of them asteroids!”

It struck me as funny—asteroids—cabbages! Nothing I could think of, could seem quite that far apart. Black, airless vacuum, rough rocks, and raw, spacial sunshine! And things from a truck garden! It didn’t match. But then, Pa Mavrocordatus didn’t match the asteroids either! He’d had a truck garden once, outside of St. Louis. And yet he was out here in space, and had been for a year and a half!

Well, even if the idea was practical, I thought first that they were still just dreaming—kidding themselves that it would be a cinch to accomplish. And not being able to fight through.

Then I glanced back at Nick. That look on his face was there again. A strange mixture of confidence, worry, grimness, and vision. It came to me then that he was no kid at all.

“LET me in on the job?” I asked hopefully.

“Sure!” Nick returned. “We wouldn’t be telling you all this, if we didn’t want you. That’s why we came back to Enter-prize—hoping to find you around some place.”

So I was in. Part of a wild scheme of progress—more thrilling and inspiring because it seemed so wild. An asteroid made into a tiny, artificial Earth! A boon to void-weary space men! A source of cheap food supplies, as well as a place to rest up. A new stage of colonization—empire building!

And then I thought I heard a sound—a faint clinking outside of the hull of the Corfu. At once, I was alert—taut. Maybe half of my sudden worry was intuition, or a form of telepathy. When you’ve been out in deep space, a million miles away from any other living soul, you feel a vast, hollow loneliness, that perhaps is mostly the absence of human telepathy waves from other minds. But when you have people around you once more, your sixth sense seems keener for the period of lack. That was why I was sure of an eavesdropper, sensing his presence. With proper sub-microphonic equipment, a man outside a space ship can hear every word spoken inside.

Nick felt it too. “But we’d better look and see,” he whispered. “Norman Haynes keeps spies around. And he may have heard rumors. You can’t keep a project like ours secret very long. It’s too big.”

My pulses jumped with fear, as I piled into my space suit. But when Nick and I got through the airlock together, there was nobody in sight. Only some footprints in the faint rocket dust of the ways, covering our own footprints, where we’d passed before, coming to the Corfu. Our flashlights showed them plainly.

“Having a rejuvenated asteroid in these parts, producing fresh food and so forth, would take a lot of trade away from the Haynes Shipping Company, wouldn’t it?” I said when we were back in the cabin once more. “Norman Haynes wouldn’t be practically boss of the Minor Planets anymore, would he? He wouldn’t like that. He’ll fight us.”

“We need you, Chet,” Irene said, her eyes appealing. That was enough for me.

“We’d better blast off right away,” Nick added. “We’re going to asteroid 487, Chet. It’s new name is Paradise. It’s the one we’ve picked.”

II

ASTEROID 487 was the usual thing. A torn, jagged, airless fragment. It was no paradise yet, unless it was a paradise of devils. Nick had a thousand men hired—space roustabouts, and a lot of mechanics and technicians, mostly fresh from Earth. Sure, it’s hard handling a bunch like that, but there was nothing in this difficulty that we didn’t know was part of the job. Some of our outfit gave us horselaughs, but they worked. The pay was good.

The ships came through with the packed loads of machinery. Atomic forges blazed, purifying native meteoric iron to complete the vast gravity-generating machine, sunk in a shaft at the center of the planetoid, ten miles down. Geedeh directed most of the work. Nick and I saw that orders were carried out, swearing, sweating, and making speeches intended to inspire.

And then the trouble started.

A rocket, bringing in food, and money to pay our crews, blew up in space, just as it was coming close. The light of the blast was blinding and awesome, making even the bright stars seem to vanish for a moment. Atomic rocket fuel going up. Gobs of molten metal dripped groundward, like real meteors heated in an atmosphere which still didn’t exist.

It could have been an accident. You can’t always control titanic atomic power, and space ships fly to pieces quite frequently. But then I had a suspicion that maybe this wasn’t an accident.

Nick and I were in the open plain to see it happen. He’d just come from the airtight barracks we’d built. His face didn’t change much behind the quartz crystal of his oxygen helmet—it only sobered a trifle. While the fiery wreckage of the rocket was still falling in shreds and fragments, he spoke, his voice clicking in my receptor phones:

“Yeah, Chet.... And there’s trouble on asteroid 439, too, where our mines are located. I just got the radio message, back at the office. Sabotage, and some men killed. It seems that some of the workmen are trying to break things up for us. Harley’s in charge. I think he can handle matters—for a while.”

“I hope so,” I answered fervently. “If the work only turns out right at this end. With that ship smashed, we’ll be on short rations for a week. And we’ve lost some important machinery. The pay money’s insured, but the men won’t like the delay.”

I didn’t expect much trouble from the crew—yet. It was Irene that really helped the most—mastered the situation. She’d taken over the management of the kitchens since the start of the work.

But now she had an additional job. She talked to that rough crew of ours. “We’re going to win, boys 1” she told them. “We know what we’ve got to do: Our task is for the good of every one of us—and for many people yet to come!”

Simple, straightforward, inspiring talk. Funny what men will do for a pretty girl—against hell itself. But that wasn’t all of it. The paintings of hers, that she’d hung in our recreation room, showed what asteroid 487 could be, when we were finished with it.

Space men are the toughest kind of adventurers that ever lived. But adventurers are always optimists, sentimentalists, romanticists, no matter how hard the exterior. And space men, by the very nature of the appalling region to which they belong, believe in miracles.

THEY cheered the thought—most of those tough men. I cheered, too. But the miracle hadn’t happened yet, and in the back of my mind, there was always the fear that it wouldn’t happen. Those crags were still bleak and star-washed. Deader than any tomb! It wasn’t an impossible wonder—technically—to change all this. But perhaps it was impossible, anyway—because of Norman Haynes! He was the only person who had the power and the reason to stop all that we were attempting. The sabotage and killings must be incited by him—certain members of our crews must be in his hire. Quite probably the rocket that had blown up had been secretly mined with explosive, under his orders, too.

But there is nothing harder to fight than those subtle methods. We had no proof, and no easy means of getting it. We could only go on with our task. Geedeh and the rest of us worked hopefully. One segment of asteroid 487, had been part of the surface of that old world that had exploded. From here we spread the dry soil over the planetoid’s jagged terrain, drawing it in atom trucks. More soil was brought in from other asteroids. The great rock-roasting furnaces were put up. Gypsum was heated in them, releasing its water in great clouds of steam, which the artificial gravity kept from drifting off into space. Some of the water, under electrolysis, yielded oxygen. Nitrogen came from nitrates.

Our gravity machine needed readjustments now and then. To a large extent, the thousands of parts that composed it were electrical. Great coils converted magnetic force into gravitation.

One ship reached us all right, bringing seeds and food. Another didn’t. It blew up in space, the second to go. Then somebody tried to get Geedeh, the Martian, with a heat ray. Another food ship failed to arrive.

Then Norman Haynes came to visit us. He landed before he had a chance to refuse to receive him. He had a body-guard of a dozen men. He was our enemy, but we couldn’t prove it. He seemed to have forgotten the little brush between himself and me, at his office.

“Splendid layout you’ve got, Wallace and Mavrocordatus!” he said to Nick and me, pronouncing Nick’s name perfectly. He sounded very much like his usual self. “Of course there’s bound to be difficulties. Trouble with crews, and so on. It’s hard to get people to believe in a project as fantastic as this. I didn’t quite believe in it, either, at first. But the facts are proved, now that the groundwork is laid. You’ll need help, fellows. I can give it to you.”

He was smiling, but under the smile I could see a snaky smirk, which probably he didn’t know showed. I felt fury rising inside me. He was trying to get control of our project, now that he saw for sure that it could amount to something. Competition he feared, but if he had control he could enforce his high prices, keep his empire, and expand his wealth by millions of dollars. His dirty work must have been partly an attempt to force the issue.

“Thanks,” Nick told him quietly. “But we prefer to do everything alone.”

Our visitor shrugged, standing there at the door of his space boat. “Okay,” he breezed. “Get in touch with me, if you feel you need me!”

Some hours later, a radiogram came through from Earth. “Congratulations!” it read. “Stick to your guns! I like people with imagination. Maybe I’ll be back in harness soon myself.—Art Haynes.”

“HE’S probably just being sarcastic,” I said bitterly.

“Old devil!” Pa Mavrocordatus growled.

Two men were killed just thirty minutes after the message was received. A little thin-faced fellow named Sparr did it, But he got away in a space boat before we could catch him. A paid killer and trouble maker.

The incident put our crew more on edge than before. A half dozen of the newcomers—mechanics from Earth—quit abruptly. Our food was almost gone. We got another shipload in, but the growing unrest didn’t abate, though we kept on for another month. There was similar trouble on 439, where the Mavrocordatus money came from. But maybe we’d make the grade, anyway.

We had a pretty dense atmosphere already, on Paradise Asteroid. The black sky had turned blue now. The ground was moist with water. Earthly buildings were going up. Pa Mavrocordatus had had seeds and small trees and things planted. It was that deceptive moment of success, before the real blow came.

After sunset one night, I heard shots. I raced out of the barracks, Geedeh, Irene, and Pa Mavrocordatus following me. We all carried blast tubes.

We found Nick in a gorge, his body half burned through, just above his right hip. But he was still alive. He had a blast tube in one hand. Two men lay on the rocks and earth in front of him, dead. Beside them, glinting in our flashlight beams, was an aluminum cylinder.

“It’s a bacteria culture container, Chet,” Nick whispered. “They had me caught, and they bragged a little before I did some fast moving, and got one of their blast tubes. Venutian Black-Rot germs. They were going to dump them in the drinking water supply. They mentioned—Haynes....”

Nick couldn’t say much more than that. But he’d saved our lives. He died there in my arms, a hero to progress, a little breeze in the new atmosphere he’d helped to create rumpling his curly hair. He’d died for his dream of beauty and betterment.

Poor little Irene couldn’t even cry. Her face was white, and she was striken mute. Her pa was shaken by great sobs, and he babbled threats. I told him to shut up. Geedeh cursed in his own language, his voice a soft, deadly hiss, his little fists clenching and unclenching.

“Too bad Nick had to kill these men!” I growled. “We could have made ’em talk. We’d have evidence. The law would take care of Norman Haynes!”

“But we ain’t got nothing!” Pa Mavrocordatus groaned. “Nothing!”

Geedeh’s face was twisted into a Martian snarl of hate. Irene stared, as though she were somewhere far away. I tried putting my arm around her, to bring her back to us. It was a minute before she seemed to realize I was there.

“Irene,” I said. “I love you. We all love you. Buck up, kid. We can’t quit now—ever! We’d be letting Nick down.”

She just nodded. She couldn’t talk.

A COUPLE of hours later I was meeting our workers in our office. Most of them tried to be decent about it. “We’d like to stick, Wallace. But how can we? Nothing to eat....” That was what most of them said, in one way or another.

And how could I answer them?

Some were not so regretful, of course. Some were downright ugly. A little crazy with space perhaps, or else hopped up with propaganda that secret agents in Haynes’ hire had been spreading among them.

“Why should we work for you anyway?” they snarled. “Even for good money, most of which we haven’t collected? You’re probably like what we’re used to. Just fixing up another place here, to clip us in the end, charging us prices sky high. Your ‘Paradise’ is just a little fancier, that’s all.”

So they turned away, and the exodus began. The freight ships blasted off, one by one, with loads of men. We couldn’t stop them. And soon the silence closed in. We were left alone to bury Nick. The small sun was bright on the rough pinnacles, and their naked grey stone was bluely murky in the new air. There was a humid warmth of summer around us.

Just then, I didn’t even feel exactly angry, in the blackness of failure, Norman Haynes had won, so far. What would be his next step in completing our final defeat?

I spent some time in the office, going over records. Presently Pa Mavrocordatus came rushing from the barracks. His whole fat body sagged, as he paused before me. His face was like paste. He didn’t seem quite alive.

“Irene,” he croaked. “She’s gone... too....”

I ran with him to her quarters There was some disorder. A picture of her mother was tipped over on a little metal dressing table. A rug was rumpled, and there was some clothing scattered on the floor. That was all.

Geedeh had entered her quarters, too. “Kidnapped,” he hissed.

What Haynes meant to accomplish by having his agents, carry off Irene, I couldn’t imagine. The hate I felt blurred all but the thought of getting her back to safety. The urge was like a dagger-point, sharp and clear in the chaos of memories. I knew how much she meant to me now.

“I need a rocket,” I said quietly. “The fastest we’ve got. I want to radio the Space Patrol, too.”

“There are no ships left here,” Geedeh returned. “The men took them all, except a little flier, which they meant us to have. But somebody has smashed it. Our big radio transmitter is smashed, also.”

A minute later I was clawing in the wreckage of tubes and wires, there in the radio room. The apparatus was completely beyond repair. For the time being we were helpless, stranded on our asteroid. For a moment I felt little shouts of madness shrieking in my brain. But Geedeh’s stabbing glance warned me that this was not the way. I fought back, out of that flash of mania.

“We’d better break out all of our weapons, Geedeh,” I said. “Haynes has gone too deep to back out now. He’s in danger of the Patrol if we talk, so he’ll have to strike at us soon.”

Thus we prepared ourselves as well as we could, for attack. Geedeh, Pa Mavrocordatus, and I. We equipped ourselves with our best armament—atomic rifles. Pa Mavrocordatus had gotten over most of his confusion. He was still sick with grief, but necessity seemd to have steadied him. He clutched his rifle grimly as we took up positions behind rock masses at the edge of the landing field.

III

WE waited silently. The asteroid turned on its axis. The brief night came. Then we saw the rockets approaching—flaming in on shreds of blue-white rocket fire. As the two ships slowed for a landing, the three of us discharged a volley.

Our atomic bullets burst on impact, dazzling in the dark. The concussion was terrific.

“Got one!” I heard Pa Mavrocordatus shout after a moment, his voice thin through the ringing in my ears. My dazzled eyes saw one ship lying on its side on the landing field, its meteor armor unpunctured by our small missiles, but with its landing rockets damaged. The other ship had grounded itself perfectly.

We were ready to fire agam, when the paralytic waves swept over us. I saw Geedeh half rise, doubling backward in a rigid spasm, his rifle flying wide.

Then I knew no more, until I heard Norman Haynes speaking to us. We were bound firmly, and it was daylight again, and our captor and his score of henchmen were smirking.

“I’m just trying to.figure out how to make your deaths seem as accidental as possible,” Haynes said, looking at me. “A couple of men of mine seem to have bungled a little business of bacteria. Maybe they blabbed before you fellows killed them. Now, of course, I can’t take any chances. Too bad your reconditioned asteroid has to appear a failure for a while. But I can’t let my taking over seem too obvious. Have to wait a while. I may be able to start up something here later, when people sort of forget.”

“What have you done with Irene?” I stormed blackly.

Haynes’ look was quizzical. “Why ask me?” he answered. “She probably ran off with one of your roustabouts. Or else they decided that she’d be nice company to have around, and made her go along.”

He laughed cynically. Maybe he was telling the truth about not knowing where Irene was. But if this was true, it didn’t make me feel much better. If some of his gang, who’d been working with us, had kidnapped her, there was no telling how badly she’d fare.

My fears showed on my face, and Norman Haynes seemed to enjoy them, though he was nervous, dangerously so. It was getting daylight again, now. He kept glancing at the sky, twiddling his soft hands. He didn’t like physical danger.

“Your gravity generator seems to be the answer to my prayers, Wallace,” he informed me. “At full force it’ll develop at least fifty Earth gravities, before breaking down and melting itself. We’ve inspected it. Power like that’ll destroy all of you. It will look like an accident—a breakdown of the machinery.”

Though Pa Mavrocordatus kept cursing Haynes continuously, and Geedeh kept calling him names that no Earthman could have translated into our less vitriolic English, our captor paid them no attention. He kept directing his threats at me. That was how I knew he was still thinking of the time in his office at Enterprize, when I’d called him by his true colors. He still held that grudge, and he meant to pay me back with fifty gravities. Which means that every pound of Earth-weight would be increased to fifty pounds! In a grip like that a man as big as me would weigh a good four tons!

That meant a heart stopped by the load of the blood it tried to pump, and tissues crushed by their own weight! Like being on the surface of some dead star of medium dimensions, where gravity is terrific 1

AT Haynes’ order, six of his twenty henchmen picked up Geedeh and Pa and me. The whole bunch was an ugly looking lot, the scum of the space ports. Some of these men were commanded to stay on the surface of the planetoid, while we were carried to the elevator shed. In the cage we descended at dizzying speed to that vault at the center of 487 where the gravity machinery was housed in its crystal shell. At that depth, under the load of the column of air above, the atmospheric pressure was very high. One could not breathe comfortably in that stuffy medium.

“Courage!” Geedah gasped to Pa Mavrocordatus and me, while his great eyes kept roving around, looking for some chance that wasn’t there.

Haynes began to examine the machinery. He was smirking again. “Simple to do!” he said to his companions. Set the robot control for gradually increasing power, so that we’ll have time to get away. Break the manual controls, so that no readjustments can be made. You can cut our friends loose now, Zinder, so there won’t be any ropes to show this was a put-up job. But keep your blasters on these men—all of you!”

This was the end, all right. I was sure of it. I’d die without even knowing what had happened to Irene. Irene, whom I knew now that I loved....

We’d been freed of our bonds when the surface phone rang. The lookout party, whom Haynes had left above, was calling. Our captor snapped on the switch of the speaker. A voice boomed in that busy cavern of metal giants, green light, and glinting crystal:

“Listen, Chief! There’s a bunch of specks to the right of the sun. They’re getting bigger fast. Must be a flock of space ships. Couldn’t be any of yours. What’ll we do?”

I saw Haynes’ weak features go sallow. Briefly my spirits rose. I couldn’t imagine whom those ships could belong to. But they must be rescuers of some kind. They were coming to stop Norman Haynes’ mad-

But Haynes was clever, as he quickly proved. “Friends of Wallace here, I suppose. Maybe even Space Patrol boats,” he said over his phone to the lookout party. “You’ll all have to take a discomfort for a while. We’ll use gravity on them, too! They’ll never land successfully.”

Pa Mavrocordatus looked at me and Geedeh. “What’s he mean—use gravity?”

Geedeh was a bit quicker than I in giving the obvious answer. “Just as with us,” he said. “Increase the output of the gravity generator here to a certain degree. From space, the increase will be practically unnoticeable., The rockets will try to land—but without taking into consideration the multiplied attractive force, they will crash!”

“Many birds with one stone!” Haynes chuckled gleefully. “You will have a short reprieve, friends, while I take care of these intruders, whoever they are. I can’t use too great a gravity on them at first. It might warn them, if they notice that their ships are accelerating too rapidly. They might as well be part of my ‘accident’, even if they do happen to be police. The Space Patrol has accidents now and then, just like anybody else!”

Haynes started to work the manual controls of the generator. The area in which he and his several aides stood, was shielded against the greater attraction, having been thus arranged by us for testing purposes. The shrill hum of the machines grew louder.

I felt the weight of my prone body increase suffocatingly. The heat increased too, as the great coils, gleaming in the glow of illuminators, gradually absorbed more power. And I knew that, out in space, those slender fingers of force were reaching and strengthening, invisible and treacherous. Our unknown friends were doomed.

Not only were they doomed, but our whole idea was destined to failure. The dream that Nick had died for. The vast progress that it meant. Worlds out here—worlds with largely a self-sufficient production—real colonization. Fair play. Norman Haynes would resist all that, because progress would weaken his power here. He was master of the asteroids, because he was master of their imports and exports. And unless he could control the rejuvenated asteroids himself, they would never be. With him directing, they would not represent a real improvement—only another means of robbing from the colonists. And colonists weren’t rich.

I could see those same thoughts, that gouged savagely into my own brain, burning in Geedeh’s cat eyes, where he sprawled near me. Being a Martian, born to a lesser gravity than the terrestrial, he was suffering more than I—physically. But perhaps my mental torture was worse. Geedeh was Irene’s friend, but I loved her. She was gone—lost somewhere—maybe dead. That, for me, was the worst—much worse than that crushing weight.

I couldn’t let things remain the way they were! My seething fury and need lashed me on, even in my helplessness. God—what could I do? I tried to figure something out Could I break the gravity machinery some way? Impossible, now, certainly!

I tried to remember my high school physics. Principles that might be used to give warning signals, and so forth. And just what that awful gravity would do to things.

Close to me was the base of the domelike crystal shell that covered the gravity generator. It wasn’t a vital part, certainly, just stout quartz. But it was the only thing I could reach. As I lay there on the floor, I drew my foot back, doubling my knee. I stamped down against the quartz with all my strength. The first blow cracked it. The second drove my metal-shod boot-heel through with a crashing sound. A small hole, eighteen inches long, was made in the barrier. The sounds of the great machinery went on as before. The gravity kept slowly increasing. Geedeh, suffering more, now, looked at me puzzledly. Pa Mavro-cordatus stared anxiously. And Norman Haynes at the surface phone laughed unpleasantly.

“Cracking up, eh, Wallace?” he sneered. “I know who your would-be helpers on those space ships are, now. I suppose I should be surprised at their identities. They’re calling to you. Want to listen? My men above have looked this surface phone to our ship radio.”

He turned up the volume of the reproducer.

Irene’s voice was the first in the speaker. “Chet!” she was urging. “Chet Wallace! Pa! Geedeh! Do you hear me? I left 487 of my own free will. I couldn’t waste time, going to the Space Patrol for help—they’d want proof, and that would take a while to present. So—there was only one person and I thought you’d mistrust him.... Why don’t you answer? Or have you left 487 too? I’m turning the mike over to somebody else, now. I found him on Enterprise, just come from Earth, Mr. Arthur Haynes....”

IV

I GASPED, listening to Irene. I didn’t know what surprised and confused me most—her being alive and safe, or what she’d done about old Art Haynes. Could I trust old Art? I had no way of telling. Had Irene told him about his nephew, or had she kept silent? Did he know he was opposed to Norman Haynes, or did he think it was somebody else who had sabotaged the project? Where would his loyalties be, if he found out? It was a ticklish situation.

As soon as Irene’s ragged, excited breathing died away in the speaker, Norman Haynes took it upon himself to clarify his own stand, and my uncertainties. He looked at Geedeh and Pa and me, tense and suffering in the grip of the gravity, and tortured with doubt.

“Uncle Art is an old fool,” he said. “So he thinks he’ll come back to the asteroids, and replace me in the business, does he? Well, he should have died long ago, and now is as good a time as any! He might as well be part of the accident, too, along with those space bums of yours. Nobody’ll ever know 1”

It was tragic that old Art couldn’t have heard that. But his nephew wasn’t broad-'casting. He was just listening quietly.' And now his uncle’s voice was coming through:

“We’re blasting in to land, Wallace, if you’re listening. There won’t be any more trouble, now. I’ll see to that! We’ll find out who’s back of this sabotage. We’ll put an end to it!”

For me it was bitter, black irony—old Art proving himself our friend, now! He didn’t know his enemy. He was nearly ninety—a grim old fighter, with real vision. Irene too, who meant everything to me. She didn’t know that with the intensified gravity those incoming ships would be smashed and blazing!

My mind was growing a bit dim in the strangling pressure of the artificial gravitation. Sweat was streaming from me in the smothering heat that added to the oppressiveness of the heavy air. Pa Mavrocor-datus was groaning the name of his daughter. Geedeh’s great eyes were fixed on me in helpless suffering.

Through the shrill sounds of the engines I listened for more words from Irene and old Art. But none came. They must know their doom by now. They must be fighting savagely and hopelessly to get away. Still some distance from 487, they were already caught, deep in the web of invisible force.

After some moments, I heard a distant crash, a roll of sound. What was it? A huge rocket, hitting the jagged crags above, at meteoric speed? Crumpling, destroying itself and those inside it? I thought my heart would burst with the added weight of my anxiety.

The first crash was only the beginning. Others followed in quick succession—inexorably. And there was a faint, far-off roar, coming down from ten miles above.

And that roar was the roar of titanic rain. Of floods of water coming down this shaft, where the gravity machine was! All the countless tons of water that we’d baked from ancient rocks, and which had been mostly suspended as vapor in our synthetic atmosphere, was condensing now, coming down in torrents!

NORMAN HAYNES kept grinning satanically, while he and his aides attended to the gravity machine. Triumph showed in his eyes. But presently he began to look puzzled, as that soughing roar that accompanied the crashing din, increased. It was a little early for the space ships to be smashing up, anyway.

I could feel a grim smile coming over my lips, against my will. Had my guesses and hopes, which had seemed so unsubstantial, been correct? Norman Haynes was glancing doubtfully at the reproducer. I could see that he was wondering why his surface watchers didn’t communicate any more—and tell him what was happening up there on the crust of 487.

I knew the answers, now! Geedeh did, too. The excitement of knowledge was in his withered, pain-wracked face. Those distant crashes were not what I’d feared they might be, but part of what I’d hoped for. They were gigantic thunder-claps—the noise of terrific lightning bolts! Norman Haynes had made a simple oversight in his plan to destroy those incoming space craft. There was a fearsome electrical storm going on above—one of inconceivable proportions—utterly beyond the Earthly! Doubtless all of Norman Haynes’ surface watchers, up above, had been killed by that sudden deluge of electricity! The multiplied gravitation up there, had pinned them down, so that they could neither escape, nor warn their chief!

Before Norman Haynes understood what was happening, foam-flecked muddy water was at the door of the machinery room, rushing and gurgling past the threshold! He and his helpers stared at it stupidly, and I laughed at them.

“You didn’t realize it, did you, Haynes?” I grunted. “You didn’t realize that increased gravity would increase the weight of the atmosphere, as well as of everything else! And increased weight of the air, means increased atmospheric pressure, too, pushing molecules together, creating greater density. And what happens? Go back to your high school physics, Haynes!

It’s like when you store air in the tank of a compressor pump. The moisture in it liquifies. And in the case of an atmosphere as big as 487 has now, static electricity would be suddenly and violently condensed, besides.”

Norman Haynes stared at me, stunned with consternation. But his recovery was fairly prompt. His sudden sneer had a rattish desperation. “Hell,” he said. “Just a thunder storm. A lot of rain. What of it? The gravity machine still works. The ships will still be destroyed.”

I knew that that was true—unless what I’d planned happened. Those rockets, manned by our old construction crew, and Irene, and old Art Haynes, had been too close to asteroid 487 for the last couple of minutes, to effect an escape, even if the sudden dark clouds had warned them that something dangerous was afoot.

“Watch this—Haynes,” Geedeh panted, and it was hard for the acting head of the Haynes Shipping Company to guess what the little Martian meant, at first.

UNDER the pull of that terrific gravity, the water was coming into that room like an avalanche. Geedeh and Pa and I were floundering in it feebly, held to the floor by that awful weight. I was sure we’d drown. But as we coughed and sputtered, the flood found its way through the hole I’d kicked, low down in the side of the crystal dome that covered that gigantic machinery. There was a flash of electrical flame, as the water interfered with the functioning of the apparatus.

It was pandemonium, then. Every man for himself. Geedeh, the scientist, and I, who, under the force of grim need, had somehow contrived to plan this finale, had the advantage of knowledge. We’d figured out a little of what to do.

The gravity winked off suddenly—reaching the low of practically nothing, here at the center of this tiny world, whose normal attraction, even at the surface, was very small. We struggled to our feet, in a muddy swirl that was now a yard in depth. But before we could take advantage of our sudden lightness, and leap clear, the gravity machines gave a last gasp of power, and we were pulled down again, smothering. Then, with a grating roar, the apparatus stopped. The bedlam ceased, except for a low whine of expanding atmosphere, and screams from Haynes and his men.

Presently, I felt all hell stabbing through me. My ears rang as with the after effects of some colossal explosion. My whole body ached. I clutched at Geedeh, who seemed on the point of collapse. Pa Mavrocordatus managed to help me....

But strained by gravity vastly stronger than that of Mars, and now facing a circumstance even more dangerous, tough little Geedeh still had his wits, fortunately for us all. He pointed to an airtight crystal cage at one edge of the chamber. The cage was necessary in routine testing of the machinery here, which called for variations in the output of the gravity generators, and consequent great variations in air pressure.

“Inside the cage—all of us!” Geedeh squeaked. “Quickly! Bends!..

Do you know what the air pressure is, at the bottom of a ten-mile shaft, even at normal Earth gravity? Yeah, something pretty high! Then you can imagine what it had just been like, here, at six or seven gravities! But when the generators had quit entirely, there had been that sudden loss of weight in the air, sudden expansion, thinning, loss of pressure!

The three of us got inside the cage, and sealed the door. I spun valves. There was a hiss of entering atmosphere, and the pressure rose again, far above the norm of sea-level, on Earth. I felt better at once, but I knew it had been a close call.

We looked out at Norman Haynes and his henchmen. They weren’t drowning, now. Tottering, they stood with their heads well above the flood. It was something else that was killing them. Not suffocation, either. Their faces were bloated and congested in the glow of illuminators. Their bodies seemed to swell.

Norman Haynes raised his blast tube, as did several of the others, trying to fire at the crystal shelter where we had taken refuge. Norman Haynes must have known his failure, then. Why had it happened. How we had won. It may be that he even realized some justice in his hideous punishment. He had tried to obstruct progress and fair play.

The blast tube dropped from his fingers. He opened his mouth to shriek in his agony. But dark blood gushed forth, and, with his henchmen, he toppled back into the water.

“BENDS!” Geedeh said again. “Haynes had a worse case of bends than any deep-sea diver ever experienced.”

The flood had almost stopped, now, outside the cage. We waited. Vengeance was complete. And it wasn’t quite as satisfying as I might once have thought.

Presently they were with us. Irene. And old Art—proving that the Haynes name was still great, even though one who bore it had soiled it some. We emerged from our sealed cage, after the pressure around us was gradually lowered to normal.

“I didn’t think it was Norman who was guilty,” old Art breathed sadly when he spoke to us. “I knew he was high-handed, but I didn’t realize it was as bad as it was. I guess Norman got what he deserved,” he finished, and there were tears in his heavy voice.

We went to the surface in the elevator. We needed space suits again, up there, with the air as expanded as it was. A lot of the atmosphere was leaking away from 487, being held down only by the tiny natural gravity. But there was nothing that couldn’t be repaired and replaced.

“We must have pumps rigged to draw the water out of the vault, so that we can dry and repair the gravity machinery, and start it again,” Geedeh stated.

We started again, almost as we had done at the first, for quite a bit of the air and water had been whisked into space. We lived in space-suits for days, rebuilding and repairing the damaged machinery. Then with the aid of Art Haynes, and with extended credit now that our plans were made fully known and approved, we imported machinery to pump the water from the vault.

We hired specialists to come in, each of them with a trained crew of men to do the work that our old crews lacked the technical skill to do. Slowly, our planet of hope grew again, and there were bulletins sent through the asteroid belt that workers were wanted again on Paradise Asteroid.

The specialists left, replaced by the crews that had worked on the asteroid before. With unlimited credit, our great freighting ships piled materials in regular formation, and the returning crews set their ships down on the landing fields, the men pouring eagerly forth, ready to set up the buildings that would be the nucleus of another Earth in space.

With our old crews returned, it took about a hundred hours to accomplish this. Asteroid 487 was almost the same as before the final trouble with Norman Haynes, now, except that the air was a little thinner. But that could be quickly taken care of. Pa Mavrocordatus was working with his vineyards and trees, and his tomato and cabbage patches, again. The big trouble was all finished, now. The dream was coming true. A little Earth, fresh and green, for tired miners of the Path of Minor Planets. Space madness could never be so common now. And cheap, fresh products would be theirs.

V

IRENE and I walked in the warm night. The crews were whooping it up in the lighted barracks. Somebody was playing a harmonica. The stars were brilliant, and there were a thousand things to think of. How we’d all struggled. How Nick Mavrocordatus, had dreamed and worked and died. How once the asteroids had been a planet, with almost human inhabitants, dreaming, planning, struggling, too. Their rock carvings were everywhere.

“It’s the beginning, Chet,” Irene whispered. “Asteroid 487 is the first. But there’ll be others—other small, beautiful, living planets. There’s a lot of work to be done. And when it’s all finished that will be almost unfortunate—too tame.”

I knew what she meant. She was pioneer stuff, just as all of us were. The greatness of life was in its battles. On and on, to vaster and vaster heights. That was what had driven us into the interplanetary void in the first place.

I kissed her. “Don’t worry, Honey,” I said. “There’s no end to it. No point of final stagnation. It goes on and on. There’ll always be a frontier—something bigger to reach and conquer....”

And we looked up in awe toward the infinite stars.

THE FEATURE FLASH

By

FLASHING you the highlights on one of the men you’ve met in preceding issues—those cosmic-minded writers who help to nourish Planet Stories.

Wilbur S. Peacock came into the office the other day, to discuss a new novelette he has slated for Planet. Since it was the first time we had met him personally, and remembering the fans’ discussions about his stories, in the Vizigraph, we asked him to jot down a few facts that he thought would make an interesting Feature Flash.

This is what he told us:

I’m an old-timer when it comes to talking science-fiction. I was practically teethed on Planetary stories, starting back when Hugo Gernsback was the pioneer in the magazine field.

I just sort of graduated from reading them to writing them, along with yarns in other fields. And, frankly, I think I would prefer writing good stf-fiction to any other kind.

I’ve done a lot of travelling and studying in the past few years, primarily to enjoy living; secondarily, to give my writing that natural swing and rhythm that will get the readers’ “Okay.”

If I don’t do as well as some of the others, it’s not because I’m not trying, it’s because I just can’t. But hang around—I’ll burn up a typewriter some day, and produce a really good yarn.

I’m one of those guys who thinks the “World of Tomorrow” is being born today, and if a yarn of mine gives a new thought or conception to a person now, I shall feel amply repaid for my efforts.

On the strictly personal side, I top six feet by a couple of inches, have the kind of shape that is used as the first picture in those “before and after” ads. I’m single, classified IB by the army, and-my idea of real exercise is the raising of my voice about twice a day.

I like to write, fish, read, loaf, and read the kisses and kicks about my stuff in the Vizigraph. Incidentally, I’m a Kansan.

THE THOUGHT-MEN OF MERCURY

By R. R. Winterbotham

Hall and Upjohn had to escape from that “No-man’s-land” on Mercury. But to form a plan, they had to think—and their captors could read minds.

IT was neither night nor day, but a sort of nether world of twilight. The huge fern-like plants, flashing phosphorescence under the green corona light, seemed to close in after Cappy Upjohn and Terry Hall like prison bars in the windows of a dungeon.

Cappy, who was leading the way, paused and waited for Terry. As the huge, leonine man turned, his lips curled into a taunting smile.

Terry’s eyes moved from side to side, watching the weird shadows, dodging the sweep of the giant ferns as they moved in the wind.

“Scared!” Cappy ridiculed.

“I can’t help it!” the younger man said. “This place gives me the creeps.”

Cappy’s great laugh echoed above the howl of the winds. “This is Mercury. Half day, half night everlastingly. Right here is the battleground of roasting heat and perpetual cold. A twenty-mile strip of habitable land between two kinds of hell. What the devil did you expect, Tenderfoot?”

Cappy grunted in disgust, turned and picked his way through the ferns. Terry, his jaw set grimly, followed. Cappy had been through all this befoie. Twice he’d landed on Venus, and he’d been with the only previous expedition to Mercury. But Terry knew that fear was a human emotion, and that there were things even Cappy was afraid of.

The wind died a moment. Between an opening in the ferns Terry caught a glimpse of a ghostly face, more simian than an ape’s, less human than a man’s. At the same time he felt something that was like a breeze through his brain. A painless stab of thought,

“Cappy—look!” Terry pointed at the face peering through the opening in the ferns, and his hand clawed at the rifle he had slung over his shoulder. In all respects it was like an old-fashioned gun, but it fired a deadly bullet that was capable of complete annihilation of whatever it hit. A single bullet from a flouro-beam gun was powerful enough to wipe out a steel ball ten feet in diameter.

But Terry’s hands slipped away from his gun. He recognized his action as more than fear. It was panic.

Cappy had been too surprised at the sight of the grinning face to notice Terry’s action. Now the youth had control of himself.

“Great guns! This is something new, lad! A living creature on Mercury!”

“I tried to tell you, Cappy!” Terry said. “I’ve seen ’em. I’ve felt ’em for the past hour!”

“Felt ’em? Did they touch you?”

“It’s something I can’t describe. It’s like poking a finger into our brains. It doesn’t hurt, but it feels uncomfortable. It’s like being watched by someone you can’t see.”

Cappy’s boldness seemed to tarnish a little. A suggestion of a shudder seemed to pass over the man. He straightened and shook it off.

“Pooh! Imagination, Terry!”

Cappy took a step toward the creature. The eyes seemed to flash. Perhaps it was a reflection from the corona streamers stretching above the horizon to the west. Cappy halted as the creature seemed to shrink away.

“Hold on!” Cappy called. “Don’t go away! We’ve got to see that creature, Terry. Get it back! Can you stop it!”

There was no mistaking that the animal was intelligent. Perhaps it felt the same emotions that raced through Terry’s body.

“Let me try,” Terry said. His heart was pounding, but science had to know if intelligent life existed in Mercury’s twilight zone.

Terry stripped the gun from his shoulders and laid it on the ground. He pushed passed Cappy and walked toward the creature. Terry’s hands were extended, palms outward.

The creature hesitated. Its eyes flashed again and once more Terry felt something cold in his skull.

The ferns parted and the creature stepped out into view.

IT had two stubby legs, two long arms. Its head was pear-shaped and hairless, and its body was an ovoid ball, bloated and ugly. But its eyes were almost human except that they seemed to flash fire.

Terry halted, facing the creature.

“Terryhall of the earth!” The creature’s voice echoed through the ferns.

“You—you speak English!” The words that fell from Terry’s lips mirrored his surprise. In his mind flashed a name for this creature. Something like Zombie, the living dead.

“Not Zombie. Name is Chomby. I am not dead, not even living dead.”

“You read my mind! That’s what I’ve felt for the past hour. You were studying my thoughts, and you learned my language by reading my mind!”

Chomby’s rubbery lips tried to imitate a grin, but it achieved only a hideous travesty.

Chomby’s hand rubbed over the leathery rags he wore for clothing and reached toward the earthman. The gesture was unmistakable. Chomby wanted to shake hands. The Mercurian had been thorough in his probe of Terry’s brain. His actions were more human than Terry’s under the circumstances, for Terry was afraid.

“Nothing to fear from Chomby,” spoke the Mercurian.

Terry took the hand. It was leathery and cold.

“I am glad to meet you,” Terry said. He forced the words from his lips. “We came to mercury on a peaceful mission.”

“You’re afraid, Terryhall,” Chomby replied. “I do not intend to kill you. Nor will I hurt Cappyupjohn.”

Cappy brushed forward and shook hands with Chomby. He concealed a wince as he touched the creature’s corpselike flesh.

Then he unstrapped the caseknife he wore at his side and handed it to Chomby. “A gift of friendship,” he said.

Chomby reached awkwardly toward the knife. As he took it, the knife fell to the ground. Chomby leaned over and fumbled. He could hardly grasp the knife. Terry noted now what had been so repulsive about Chomby’s handshake. The Mercurian had no thumb.

Instead of the five-fingered hand of a human being, there were only three flabby fingers on the end of a round, gristly hand.

Terry stooped and picked up the knife. He handed it to the Mercurian who seized it in both hands and clutched it to his body.

“You want food and drink?” Chomby asked. “Terryhall and Cappyupjohn follow me to my village. Sorry I have no gift of friendship otherwise. My people are unskilled in handicraft. We can hardly make our own clothes.”

Chomby led the earthmen eastward. The shadows deepened and the sky grew dark. The stars appeared; among them the brilliant blue planet that was Earth.

Again Chomby read Terry’s thoughts.

“You come from that one?” he asked, pointing. “You are from the sky?”

Terry answered, but Chomby seemed to read the thoughts that Terry flashed through his mind.

“Spaceship. Machines. Rockets.” The Mercurian rolled the words in his mouth. “You come from a great race, Terryhall and Cappyupjohn. My people want to learn skill with our hands, to be like you.”

“It would be nice if we could read your minds,” Cappy said, tossing a glance toward Terry.

“You are suspicious men,” Chomby said. “I read your mind and I know you do not trust me. You fear a trap. That is why you carry your guns. But there is nothing to fear from Chomby’s people. You will think them very primitive.”

The cold winds lashed at the earthmen and nipped through the heavy clothing they wore. Terry and Cappy lowered a plastic windshield from their caps to protect their faces from frostbite.

Vegetation grew more scarce and at last they walked across a rocky plain toward a row of towering basalt cliffs. The feeble light that came from the outer fringe of the corona revealed a row of caves at the base of the cliffs and from these emerged a hundred or so ill-fashioned beings resembling Chomby.

The Mercurian gave no cry, nor warning of his approach. He apparently had notified his people by telepathy, for they rushed silently to meet him. Chomby lapsed into silence, turning from one of his kinsfolk to another, answering questions without speaking.

Cappy stared at the Mercurians. His leonine figure marched through the ill-shapen creatures confidently and unafraid. Doubts crept into Terry’s mind. There were too many Mercurians. Despite the powerful weapons strapped to the earth-men’s backs, they could not hope to escape imprisonment, if these savages sought to hold them.

Chomby led the men to a cave in the center of the village. He turned to Terry.

“My people think you are queer, Terry-hall,” Chomby said. “But it is evident to them that you think the same about us. But we are all one people. Terry-hall and Cappyupjohn are not the same. Terryhall is afraid, while Cappyupjohn is a man of rock. Are you not of the same race?”

“More or less,” Cappy said, deridingly. “Terry doesn’t understand you and he fears what he doesn’t understand. I’ve learned to control fear, so I am not afraid.”

“You trust us?” Chomby seemed surprise.

“No,” Cappy replied. “I don’t trust anything, but I’m not afraid of you.”

“What if we should intend to keep you here?” Chomby asked. “Terry sees himself as a prisoner, a slave. He fears he will never return to the earth.”

“I still have my gun,” Cappy Said.

“There are many of us,” Chomby said, his lips gaping again in that imitation grin. “We could overpower you and kill you.”

“I’d take some of you with me,” Cappy replied, defiantly. “I’d go out in a blaze of glory.”

CHOMBY studied the earthman. “I believe you would. In your world such a trait would be considered admirable. You are hard, Cappyupjohn, and brave. But it is not your kind that makes your, race so great. Your world is a coward’s world. It was built by men who are afraid.”

Cappy choked. “You lie!”

“We have read your minds, earthmen,” Chomby said. “We understand the civilization from the mental pictures you carry in your minds. You have great brains, but skilled as they are they are nothing in comparison with ours. It was not your brain that made your world, but your love of security. You feared wild beasts, so you killed them. You feared hunger, so you stored food. You built weapons to defend yourself against enemies. You sought out new worlds in fleeing from dangers of the old. If your race had not known fear, it would have never done these things.”

“Men died to win that security,” Cappy replied. “That wasn’t cowardice, was it?”

“They died fighting, which meant that they hoped to win. Their chance of victory was more attractive than the insecurity that would come with defeat,” Chomby replied. “My people wish to keep you here. He want to learn more about the emotion called fear that has made your civilization so great.”

“You’ll never keep us!” growled Cappy. His hand automatically touched the gun on his shoulder.

“That is the fear I speak of,” Chomby said. “You would rather die than be a prisoner. In a different way Terryhall has the same emotion. But he does not risk so recklessly. He would rather avoid the situation that makes fighting necessary. He is a brave man, too, Cappyupjohn, but in a different way.”

“He’s yellow!” Cappy said vehemently. “He’s worse than no help at all.”

The earthmen rested, but they were not left alone. Chomby seemed always to be near. Although Chomby insisted the earthmen were not prisoners, he made it plain they would not be allowed to leave for a time.

“We must study you,” he said. “In turn, you may study us.”

“I’m warning you, Chomby,” Cappy roared. “We’ll stand just so much of this thing. We’ll stay until we’ve studied you enough, but when we want to go, we’re going—or we’ll die trying.”

“That time is not here,” Chomby said, wrinkling his lips again.

THE icy mental probing of the Mercurians grew familiar to Terry and Cappy. There was nothing the earthmen could think of that these eerie, repulsive-looking creatures did not understand. That the Mercurians read Terry’s thoughts so easily was often embarrassing, for Terry knew that they were aware of his repugnance toward them, as well as Terry’s distrust and fear.

But Chomby and his people seemed to accept Terry’s opinion of them under-standingly. Not one of them made a move to remove either Terry’s or Cappy’s guns.

After a first period of mental probing Chomby urged the earthmen to instruct the Mercurians in some simple crafts. Now the earthmen enjoyed the sense of superiority that previously had been a monopoly of the Mercurians. The simplest pieces of handiwork were almost beyond, the Mercurians. The hands of these creatures, without thumbs and with stiff fingers, were clumsy. Weaving was an arduous task. Construction of a simple, primitive thatched dwelling was attempted and abandoned, when Cappy found that it would require months to complete. It was not because the Mercurians did not understand what had to be done—they knew this the instant the terrestrials pictured the idea in their minds. But the tasks were nearly impossible for the Mercurians.

Terry taught a few of the creatures to write, but the rest could not master the process, although every one of them had learned to read by watching Terry’s mind at work.

Cappy grew more contemptuous of the Mercurians as he watched their bungling efforts at the simplest human arts.

“We haven’t anything to be afraid of from these creatures, Terry,” he said.

Terry shook his head.

“They’ve got brains, Cappy. They know everything we know and a lot of things we don’t. They read us like a book. They know our thoughts before we know them ourselves.”

“It isn’t thought that wins battles. It’s power. Oh, brains help, but only when used in the application of the proper weapons. Why with our guns and fists we probably could lick this whole village. I’m sure they haven’t coordination enough to fight hand-to-hand with us singly.”

“But they’re too smart to let us out-maneuver them,” Terry said. “There’s a principle that seems to work in society that makes me afraid of these Mercurians. In the history of our own planet, it has always been the brains which exploited the brawn among men. People who thought of things usually took ascendancy over those who tried to progress by the sweat of their brow. For instance, everyone knows Columbus discovered America, but who knows the name of the man who built the ships he sailed in? LeCompton designed the first successful spacecraft, but the name of the man who tooled the intricate parts of its mechanism and made it successful has been completely forgotten.”

“You mean we’re likely to become slaves of these—these Zombies?”

“Since we came to this village they’ve changed,” Terry said. “These Zombies—as you call them—are learning fear. They see their world, lashed by cold and hot winds, freezing and roasting, as an insecure place. A violent storm might bum up their food supply, or freeze their crops. For the first time they’ve seen fear as a safeguard to their future. Now they want to build. They want places to store food; homes to protect them from cold. They want means of transportation, to escape uninhabitable spots. They know the value of fear, but they cannot conquer it because they are physiologically incapable of conquering their environment. When they realize this—if they don’t realize it already—they’ll force us to conquer their environment for them. Every earthman unfortunate enough to land on Mercury will become a slave—”

“Great Scott, Terry!” Cappy exclaimed. “I believe you are right. Your fear has been warning us all along to get out of this place. Get your gun ready, we’re going back to the space ship—”

The light from the entrance of the cave was blotted out. Chomby stood before them, followed by a horde of his fellow beings.

“You recognized fear too late, Cappyup-john,” Chomby said.

The two earthmen tried to level their guns, but the Mercurians attacked too quickly. The leathery fists struck home and the guns slipped from the earthmen’s grasps.

A TRANSFORMATION occurred in front of the row of caves in the basalt cliff. Windbreaks appeared in the openings in the wall. Rude machines were set up to build houses of stone and covered passages from cave to cave. From the fibrous ferns Terry constructed rude looms for weaving cloth. Stone mills for grinding the pulpy fruit of the Mercurian trees into flour were designed.

How long the two ear.thmen had been prisoners on Mercury they had no way of telling, for there was neither night nor day, nor seasons in the twilight zone. But the Earth had disappeared over the south horizon and reappeared in the north and Cappy estimated that two-thirds of the Mercurian year of 88 days had passed.

“We won’t be here another year,” Terry said.

Cappy snorted. “I wouldn’t bet.”

“They’re getting careless,” Terry pointed out. “They used to have a dozen men guarding us day and night. If we even got a little too far away from the village, we’d be shoved back. Now only one Zombie is guarding us. We’re allowed to go almost anywhere, except near the spaceship.”

“They read our minds, so they’re always two jumps ahead of us, Terry. No. The principle of brains over brawn can’t be beaten. We’re licked.”

“I’m not,” Terry announced. “Once you called me a coward—you said I was yellow. But a coward isn’t the man who is afraid, it’s the man that lets fear get the upperhand. You’re being a coward now, Cappy. You’re admitting that Chomby and his pals have the Injun sign on us. I’m not admitting it. It isn’t brains that makes men the rulers of nine planets, and it isn’t fear. Man has something else that gives him a physiological edge. I’m going to find out what that is. When we find it, we’ll be free men again.”

“When you find it, the Mercurians will know. They’ll be ready to keep us from using the weapon—whatever it is—before we know we’ve got it.”

“Some day we’ll have a chance. Some day we’ll have a chance to slug our guard and get back to the spaceship—”

Terry paused. He looked at the dozing Mercurian at the mouth of the cave. Even as Terry looked the Mercurian roused out of his sleep. The thought thread had roused the guard from a deep slumber.

“Now!” Terry yelled. “Now’s our chance!”

Terry sprang. The guard tried to seize the stone club at his side, but his clumsy hand was not made for swift action. Terry was on him before the guard could send out a mental alarm and the young earthman’s fist crashed against the base of the guard’s skull.

Terrestrial muscles, built for a heavier force of gravity, delivered a sledgehammer blow. The guard toppled forward. Terry leaped over the figure and darted into the open.

Another figure rose before Terry, but again Terry’s fist smashed.

Cappy was beside Terry now and together they raced toward the path that led in the direction of the spaceship.

“They’ll follow us!” Cappy said. “They can trail us by our thoughts. If we miss the ship and have to double back, we’ll run into them.”

“We won’t miss!” Terry said.

THE sudden formulation of the escape plan had been too quick for even the Mercurian brains to block. Terry and Cappy were racing into the forest of ferns far ahead of their pursuers. The coordinated muscles of the earthmen were far more capable of traveling swiftly than those of the Mercurians behind and sounds of pursuit grew fainter in the distance.

But Terry knew that these creatures were dogged. They would follow until the spaceship’s rockets blasted loose from the planet.

“Remember,” Terry whispered, “don’t act on any set plan. Don’t plan what you’ll do when you meet ’em. If you do they’ll be prepared for it. Act on impulse, before they know what you intend to do.”

“I’ll remember,” Cappy panted.

Was it impulse that made terrestrials the masters of the universe? Terry wondered. It hardly seemed logical, yet impulse had given them their first chance of freedom. But impulse might lead them astray. First thoughts are not always the best thoughts. True enough, man had made some strides by accident, but far more of his greatest discoveries and most useful inventions had been the result of years of labor and careful planning. No, it wasn’t impulse. Some other weapon had to be used to defeat the Mercurians decisively. Terry and Cappy might escape through luck, but some day there would be a final, decisive battle that would employ the one thing that gave man an advantage over the semi-human monsters of the first planet.

Terry hoped he could discover that weapon now.

They had been over the route to the spaceship three times. Once in company with Chomby on their first trip to the Mercurian village. They had returned in company with a guard and come back again later.

Terry had noted a few landmarks and now he began to spot them again. A curious-shaped rock; a spring of moulten metal; a deep fissure in the soil.

But as they traveled toward the sun’s corona the air grew warmer. Vegetation became profuse and the trail was more difficult to find. But Cappy had kept his eyes open, too. Between them they made their way, slower and slower.

Suddenly Terry stopped. An icy finger had passed over his brain. A wordless thought flashed into his consciousness.

“This is Chomby, Terryhall. Go back, or you will be unmercifully killed.”

Cappy looked at Terry. The same thought had flashed through his brain.

“I am ahead of you, earthmen. I am waiting in front of the spaceship. In my hands I hold a flourobeam gun. You cannot pass me, earthmen!”

Cappy groaned.

“They’re still two jumps ahead, Terry! They’ve outfigured us again. They knew we might get away by accident. So they put Chomby out here to intercept us and he’s armed with our weapons!”

Terry was afraid. He knew the power of a flourobeam. He’d seen it blast rocks into powder and he knew that a man could never survive its charge. One blast from the gun could wipe out all trace of Terry and Cappy.

Terry’s face paled. Then, suddenly, he moved forward.

“Come on, Cappy! You said I was yellow once. Let’s see who’s yellow now!”

“But that gun! This isn’t being brave! It’s foolhardy. The better part of valor is knowing when you’re licked.”

“Come on,” Terry said, moving ahead.

“You’re a fool, Terry,” Cappy said. “But you’ve got guts! Now listen to reason!”

But Terry would not listen. He moved forward. Cappy, sweating, came following.

“It’s suicide!” cried the older man.

IN the center of a clearing stood the spaceship. The streaks of the corona revealed a figure, huge, hideous and apelike, standing before the locks.

It was Chomby, holding the flourobeam gun, aiming at the two terrestrials who emerged from the forest

“If you come closer, I’ll shoot!” It was a thought, not a voice, that flashed toward the men, but the words were as clear as if Chomby had spoken.

“We’re licked, Terry!” Cappy said. “I’ll surrender.”

Slowly Cappy’s hands went over his head.

“And what about you, Terryhall?”

Terry stood in the clearing, looking at the Mercurian. The young man’s face was pale and green beneath the corona glow.

“This is a war of the worlds, Chomby,” he said. “It’s a fight between your race and mine. It’s a Waterloo for one of us.”

“You haven’t a chance, Terryhall. You know the power of this gun.”

Terry’s lips tightened into a thin, straight line. His body crouched for an instant and then he sprang. The terrestrial muscles sent him shooting toward Chomby. His feet touched the ground again, and like steel springs he shot forward a second time.

Chomby’s fingers tightened on the trigger of the weapon. They seemed to twitch.

Cappy closed his eyes.

An inhuman scream rent the Mercurian air. But the gun did not go off.

Cappy opened his eyes to see Terry and the monster rolling on the ground. Terry’s fingers were closed about the Mercurian’s throat. Chomby struggled feebly, and then lay still.

Terry rose, picked up the gun and motioned to Cappy.

“Put down your hands and start moving your legs. Get into those locks before the rest of them get here!”

Cappy’s jaw worked up and down, but words did not come from his throat. Somehow he moved. He ran into the locks and a moment later he was at the controls.

“Let ’er go!” Terry said.

Cappy, still speechless, pressed the charger. The rockets roared. The machine lurched skyward and Mercury was left behind.

“What happened?” Cappy asked.

“I just remembered that when we were last carrying the guns we had the safety catches on. The catches are released with the thumb. Chomby couldn’t do it! He couldn’t have shot me, even though he wanted to. The safety catches are such a small piece of the flourobeam mechanism that we never think of them. Chomby didn’t have a chance to read our minds about the safety catch until it was too late.”

“Terry,” Cappy said. “I’ll take back everything I said about you being yellow. You’ve got guts! More than I have, Terry.”

“Guts? Hell, Cappy, I was scared to death every second.”

THE VIZIGRAPH

SO here we are again, you vizifans, with a bundle of kicks, kudos, bombs and bouquets for our expert operator to take in his galactic stride.

We like your letters, particularly the ones that make constructive suggestions and criticisms about Planet Stories. So send them in; we’ll take a look, and pass on the ones that we believe to be the cream of the crop. The race for win, place and show in the Summer futurity just about forced a photo-finish.

But at the finish, the letters ranked like this:

1—D. C. Montgomery, Jr., 2—Mrs. Margaret Wells, 3—Bill Stoy.

CHOOSE YER WEPPONS, GENTS!

The Chastleton, #222
Washington, D. C.

Dear Editor:

Yeaaaah man! Jive—jive—jive—splutter, bombast and boasts. Several pages of ditto ad nauseam (which has been condensed for convenience in printing).

There! Now that I’ve taken care of that (the winning of the coming sweepstakes, I mean) I'll continue with my epistle.

Frankly it looks like you have to inaugurate a new language to place in this business anymore. And here I am gnashing my molars to the gums on account of missing the deadline with my last letter. My best letter to date—I felt—it was written in Sanskrit. Oh well, procrastination is the thief of Planet illustrations. Lord help me if I were writing letters for a monthly publication. Of course I might make a bi-monthly????

Third place? I should kick, with the competition getting as stiff as it is. Thanks, peoples, for the votes. Haven’t any cigars, like Asimov, and I don’t go in for political smooching. However, I do have a carton of Avalon cigarettes and a batch of autographed rejection slips. Come, let’s all pull for first place this time.

Comes now the usual. Best cover to date, which remark is becoming consistent with every new issue of Planet. Saunders draws good babes. If we’re going to have women on the cover (and we evidently are) let him or Finlay do ’em. I was a bit disappointed with the Spring wench.

Worst prize in illustrations goes to Hoskins. He must have recently graduated from Terrible Tales or sumsuch, but I think he better go back for a P.G. course. He’s not quite ready for Planet, but give him another chance anyway.

First prize in illustrations—Lynch on page 71. Even though the crack-up doesn’t look like an “unbelievable shambles,” and I can’t figure out what the babe is sticking her head out for (symbolical, perhaps?) it’s the best of his work so far. Following in order: Morey on p. 83, Leydenfrost on p. 21, Morey on p. 59, Paul on p. 43 (a come back?), Leydenfrost on p. 3, and Morey (I think) on p. 31. (I know—these parentheses look like the devil, but I don’t how else to slip it in—I throw in too many commas, anyhow).

This is about the hardest issue to rate since I’ve been reading P. S. The average is so high it’s hard to pick first place in the stories.—The pause here is for three hours consumed in tearing at my tonsorial appendage and biting my nails off, up to the elbows, trying to figure out who rates first.

After weighty deliberation (and notice the improvement in my typing, since I’ve been using my elbows) I bestow the laurel wreath to Dirk Wylie for Asteroid of the Damned. The plot wasn’t breath-taking, and I think it rates because of the characterization. My only complaint is on the Chinese money belt. I read the story over again, but couldn’t find the trace of a plant for this denouement Some more observant fan will probably pop up with it, but I couldn’t find it.

Task to Lahri takes the strongest possible second place, in fact, I’m still wondering why not first. The look-over-your shoulder-and-under-the-bed complex engendered by the unwordly atmosphere was the best in a long time.

Although I think Mr. Hasse’s letter is almost better than his story, Out of this World takes third place for the ability to create pictures or scenes in my mind as I read. (Which aforementioned fact is the test of fire, or sumpun’. Lord help us if this starts another Asinine affair 1)

Captain Chaos and Cosmic Derelict take fourth together. Broome seems to me a great deal like Bond, but this is not an accusation—just an opinion.

Fifth place to Smith for As it Was, although the “z” business almost wore me to a frazzle reading it. (Try reading it out loud, that’s fun

Mr. Wellman didn’t quite click with me this time. I usually like his work, and I can’t exactly put my finger on the reason I didn’t like this one, yet... sixth.

If all the stories in the magazine were by Cummings, The Star Master would take first place, however, there was only one, so unfortunately he gets the back door again.

Grandiloquent Gifford’s celestial cartoon series commences commendably, in fact, should be a smashing success. But don’t tell me they’re going to replace the Feature Flash.

Comes the sweepstakes and first place for Henry (that’s to make up for the rating on the story, and—ha ha ha—remember?) Second to Stoy. His idea of an organization for Vizi-grapheers has been curdling in my cranium for some time. I almost broached the subject myself. Come on, fellas’, how about it? Think we can do anything with it? I’ll volunteer mv services—for what they’re worth—in any capacity. Third place to the Happy Genius, for his cunning conceit.

This last chapter of my book is devoted to a re-hash of my missive that missed. It will probably be cut by Ye Editore, but I hated to see so much concentrated cogitation condemned to circumduction.

When I picked up my first copy of Planet I hesitated some time before buying it. Then the reckless bucaneering spirit that lurks within every reader of science-fiction said: “Go ahead! It’s only twenty cents! Take a chance 1” Reading merrily along, I finally passed the portals of the Vizigraph. Well! Well! And WELL! For my twenty cents I not only got an interesting magazine, but at the same time became eligible in this business of taking cracks at editors, authors, readers and illustrators. What more could you ask for such a small investment? And so—I joined the army of Vizigrapheers.

A short while back I remember one reader who would spend his last two dimes for our beloved alma maga, instead of stuffing himself with a double double chocolate soda. At the time I canted a quizzical eyebrow at the fellow—now, I agree with him heartily.

Part of the other letter was a protest about certain magazines, but realizing it might be libel, I’ll censor part of it. No! This is getting too long already, I’ll cut it out.

A brief essay on editors and then I’ll shut up and crawl into a hole until the next issue. (Somebody will probably be glad to dig one for me.)

The editors of some of these magazines have tried to get the spirit of fellowship, camaraderie, hail-fellow-well-met, or what have you into their reader departments, etc., but I feel they tried too hard or something. At least they don’t make it

Planet Stories has an editor who has achieved perfection in this business of descending from Olympus to shake hands with mere mortals. The mixture of interest, cordiality and perhaps we can even say camaraderie, has made (and is making) Planet the best magazine in the field. And if anybody wants to argue it out, the line forms on the left for bops on the beez-ers and on the right for nasty letters.

Hasta la vista, Amigos?
William A. Conover.

VOKANTA KANADON!

Box 6475 Met. Sta.,
Los Angeles, Cal.

Kara Redaktisto:

Saluton! Kaj hola Sinjoro Goldsmith. This is the voice of MOROJO, calling Canada... in response to your paging me in the Vintra (Winter) edition of PS.

Few facts about myself? “Morojo” is derived from the initials of my maiden name, according to the Esperanto alfabeto, with a decisive “d” soffend to “j,” which in the tung of tomoro equals the English “y.” Thus my adopted name is pronounced: Mo-ro'yo.

I am a “proto-J” of the famous 4sJ, World Stfan No. I and my mentor. He made me what I am today, I hope he’s satis fyd! I was familiar with science fiction bfor 4e was born, but I never payd attention to authors, readers’ columns or clubs til Fojak (that’s his Esperanto name) came along and turnd me into a fan.

Now I have a collection of hundreds of professional magazines and hundreds more of the fan, co-edit Voice of the Imagination and Novacious, have attended over 150 meetings of the Los Angeles Science Fantasy Society, am Librarian of the Shangri-LA group, been to both the Nycon and Chicon (New Yo.-k and Chicago Science Fiction Conventions) and am member No. 2 of the organization sponsoring 1941’s convention in Denver (the Denvention). I have seen such authors as Ray Cummings, Eando Binder, Ed Earl Repp, Nelson S. Bond, Ross Rocklynne, Henry Kuttner, Helen Weinbaum, Dr. Keller, Ray Palmer, Manly Wade Wellman, Edmond Hamilton, Ralph Milne Farley, Harl Vincent and Jno W. Campbell, Jr. I noe Robt. Heinlein per-sonly, have danced with Jack Williamson at Earl Carroll’s, tho I can scarcely believe it, have spoken with Paul “Skylark” Smith and H. G. Wells!

Thanx for the intrest in me. Bon-sancon k sukceson al PLANED-FABELOJ!

Morojo.

VAMPIRE QUEEN

By Thornton Ayre

“I'm mightier than the law!” Valcine Drew, Vampire Queen of the Starways, flung her challenge at the Interplanetary Patrol. Curt Stanley accepted the challenge—and stepped directly into a Jovian space-trap from which there was no escape.

I HAD been wondering for some little time why the Chief had summoned me with such urgency. However, being a well trained special agent of the Interplanetary Police I knew my place and kept quiet while he went through his papers, and generally attended to matters which were of no concern to me.

Then at length he glanced through the huge windows of the office and motioned me to his side.

“See her?” he asked quietly, nodding outside.

Here on the ground floor of the building we had a clear view of the square outside. The building opposite belonged to the Consolidated Trust, one of the biggest financial groups in the world and virtual backers of the Interplanetary Corporation itself.

Just emerging from the building was a slender girl in a cornflower blue costume of the time. She was blonde—flaxen blonde almost—and wore no hat. I could see her features were acquiline; her manner alert and decisive.

“What of her?” I asked the Chief presently, puzzledly.

“Ever see a woman without a soul, Curt?” the Chief asked me seriously, his lips tightening. “If not, now’s your chance. That is Valcine Drew—or if you prefer it, ‘The Granite Angel’.”

I began to understand. Valcine Drew—mystery woman, incredibly wealthy—known among the lower dives by her queer appelation because she traveled the starry ways and was reputed to be inhumanly cruel.

It is never easy to reconcile beauty and viciousness; I certainly couldn’t manage it in regard to this lovely girl.

“I’ve something to tell you about her,” the Chief went on, watching her. “From the private reports I have received it is more than clear that she is dodging the law somewhere. Take a good look at her: later you may need to meet her at closer quarters.”

We watched her finally get into a sleek atomic roadster and make off for parts unknown. Cruel? Ridiculous! I began to suspect the Chief had gotten a bad dose of suspicion from the reports he had received.

Then he crossed over to his desk, motioned to me. There was no doubt of the gravity of his expression.

“Valcine Drew is a menace,” he said. “From somewhere in space she keeps obtaining critanium mineral. Not just a few grams at a time but whole pounds of it! How she gets it is the mystery, and that is why we suspect it must be illegal. Naturally she sells it to the Trust and because of its immense value they buy it without question. But since we represent the law we have to look into it. It’s a knotty problem to solve how she gets the stuff because our own ways of getting it demand skilled engineers. The stuff can only be obtained from Jupiter so far as we know, and Jupiter is a living hell as you realize. Twice a year our engineers get some of the mineral from there, and more often than not lose fifty percent of their men doing it. But this girl secures the stuff incessantly! How, I can’t imagine. And it is your job, Curt, to find out.”

I nodded slowly, thinking. “The only critanium deposits known to us are of course on Jupiter. It’s inconceivable that she’d risk that deadly planet every time. Maybe she has found deposits of it somewhere else?”

“Maybe; but the fact remains the source isn’t registered in the interplanetary claim files and it ought to be. So, it comes under the heading of piracy. Find out what she’s up to. Get busy!”

I rubbed my chin thoughtfully. To tell me to get busy was one thing: how to start was another. Evidently the Chief guessed my thoughts for he added, “Her ship will probably be at the Main Spaceport—the Silver Eagle. She takes on a fresh crew every trip, perhaps to prevent any one crew from getting too familiar with her ways.”

“But can’t you find out from a member of a dismissed crew what she’s up to?”

“No. Fear of her striking back keeps mouths utterly sealed; and as yet we have no authority to make anybody speak. We need evidence. Your best course is to get yourself hijacked onto that ship and then figure out best how to get the proofs we need.”

I nodded understanding’ and then shortly took my leave.

I’d been seated an hour, soaking in thick weed smoke and listening to the buzz of conversation around me, when things began to happen. The doors of the saloon suddenly sprang open and a man in immaculate blue uniform appeared. He stood with his arms at his sides just staring round.

He was quite the ugliest man I had ever seen. His face was square, brutally strong, with a projecting jaw scarred down one side. The lips were tight, unyielding: the eyes that gazed under the shiny peak of his Cap were frosty blue. If one could forget the bullying, swaggering air he adopted, it had to be admitted he was a fine man—well over six feet and proportionately broad.

“Know him?” whispered the out-of-work engineer next to me. “That’s first-mate Casper of the Silver Eagle, as tough a nut as ever prowled a catwalk.”

“Stop your jabbering here for a minute !” Casper roared suddenly, glaring round. “Don’t you know your damned manners when there’s a lady around? Shut your traps, all of you!”

The quiet that followed was more of astonishment than respect for his command—astonishment at the sight of the lovely girl in blue who came in beside him. I watched her intently, noting how she entered this den of riffraff without the least timidity. Indeed she moved with urgency and authority, stood looking round on us all with supreme contempt.

Beyond a doubt she was beautiful; oval faced, flaxen-haired. But I began to understand something of what the Chief had said now I came to study her at close quarters. It was a face without a single redeeming quality of sentiment about it. It was cold, inhuman, granite indeed. And her eyes I noticed were a deep sea-green, enhanced if anything by fair, curling lashes and eyebrows.

“I want twenty men!” Her voice suddenly rang over the silence with the clearness of a bell. “And I said men! No namby-pamby rubbish for me. I want men of iron who’ll battle the toughest fields in the spaCeways; men who’ll risk death. Twenty, I said. And you’ll each be paid a thousand dollars apiece for the trip out and back. Let’s have your offers.”

She folded her arms and waited in insolent expectation. The man next to me grinned cynically.

“Not for me!” he murmured. “A thousand dollars to work under that she-cat and Casper. Not damned likely!”

“Work for the Granite Angel?” breathed another. “Hell, no!”

Casper’s voice roared forth again. “What in hades has gotten into you? Unbutton your uncivil tongues and speak up! You heard the offer—thousand dollars for the round trip. Step up, and quick! If you don’t I’ll—”

“Well, you’ll what?” yelled a derisive voice. “We got rights, remember, and you can’t alter ’em!”

Casper’s face Colored rapidly and he took a step forward; but the girl restrained him. She looked round again and repeated her offer. At that one or two men began to rise and slowly make their way forward. To them no doubt a thousand dollars was worth plenty of grief, so when half a dozen or so had got on the move I joined too, shuffled along in my rubber space shoes until I was finally face to face with Casper.

“Name?” His flinty gaze swept me up and down.

“Stanley Curtis,” I said, reversing my names. “Rocket hand.”

“Here’s your papers,” he said brusquely, thrusting a bunch of identification sheets in my hand. “Take ’em to Main Spaceport and get aboard the Silver Eagle. Quick as you can. We take off at sundown.”

I nodded, cast a sidelong look at the girl. All I got was the icy stare of her green eyes. I shambled out, puzzling to myself. The even closer look I had had of her face had convinced me her expression was more forced than natural: it was as though she were laboring under some immense tension or other. Had she relaxed only for a moment I could have imagined her as little short of adorable. Granite Angel, eh? It got me wondering.

I GOT aboard the Silver Eagle and went down into the rocket hold, that stifling quarter in the ship’s belly where none but riffraff and special agents are ever found. With the other sullen-faced men I went about the job of attending to my particular rocket junjit, getting it all in order for the departure signal from the control room above.

After a while it came, in Casper’s full throated bellow.

Off we went, our only indication of flight down here being the pressure of the gravity on the floor. It held us down for a moment or two as we made steady upward climbing; then it relaxed a little. We settled down to our job, sweating heavily.

Presently I left the others and went to the outlook port. No reason why I shouldn’t: I had done all required of me at the unit for the moment. I stared out into space. Earth was dropping from us far below, and to right and left of us were Venus and Mars. They too were receding : clearly they were not intended as our destination. Jupiter was perhaps the answer after all, twinkling far away in the star-sprinkled backdrop.

Then suddenly the view was shut off as the steel slide of the port slammed shut. I had a vision of a blue coated arm clamping the combination lock. I twisted round to stare into Casper’s square, grimly smiling face.

“Get back to your work,” he ordered in •a low voice. “Get back, before I beat the living daylights out of you! What do you think this is, a tour?”

“What’s wrong with looking outside?” I asked Calmly.

“Plenty so far as you’re concerned! You’re here to tend a rocket unit, not pry into things that don’t concern you! Get moving!”

With a shrug I returned to my task, but there were murmurings from others among the crew. One remark evidently reached Casper for he swung round and came forward, hand resting on the butt of his flamegun.

“What was that you said?” His eyes blazed inquiry.

“I said who in hell do you think we are!” repeated one of the men. “We’ve the right to see where we’re goin’, ain’t we?”

“Not on this ship you haven’t! Your best course is to keep your trap shut and your mind on your job. It’ll be healthier for all of you. Besides—”

Casper broke off and stood aside as the girl herself appeared at the top of the ladder. She came slowly down, looked round on the men.

“Trouble?” she asked Casper shortly.

“They don’t like the window shields being drawn,” he sneered. “Maybe they’d like a few feather beds to lie on too!”

The girl’s stony gaze settled on us. “Perhaps my first-mate hasn’t made things quite clear to you,” she said slowly; “so I will. You will get your money when the trip is over. For that money you’ll sweat your guts out down here watching these rockets. On board this ship there are no pryings and peepings. You’re here to work to the full, and under my command you’ll do it. If any man dares to show a hint of mutiny, or is found slacking on the job, he’ll be punished without mercy. I don’t mean irons; I don’t mean solitary. I mean death!”

I looked up at her sharply. “You haven’t the authority to do that!”

“The law gives the master of the ship entire jurisdiction,” she retorted. “On this ship there is only one law—Mine!” Then she stood eying me reflectively and added, “You sound pretty educated for an ordinary rocket hand. What are you doing here?”

“Money doesn’t last forever,” I said evasively.

SHE pondered that, her green eyes piercing me. Then with a final warning glance round she retreated up the ladder with Casper behind her. The trap slammed down. Not only that: it was locked. We were virtually imprisoned down in this hell hole with no conception of how to get out of it.

The big fellow who’d complained spat suddenly. “The dirty sun-fried hell-cat! I’ll be damned if I’ll stand for it! There are rules on all ships!”

“An’ a special one for the ship run by the Granite Angel,” commented another dryly. “I say we should lie low and stop trying to quiz. It’s sticking out our chins.”

This started an argument in which I’d no wish to take part. I had my own immediate problems to work out. The closing of the windows and trap door suggested important moves afoot, moves significant enough to be shut off from a crew anyway. It was essential I see something of what was destined to happen. How to get out of here, though? I looked around me for some sort of weapon with which to perhaps pry the trapdoor, or else unseal the window. But I found nothing.

THIS problem occupied my mind for a long time afterwards, through several work and rest periods indeed, during which time we must have covered enormous distances across the gulf. Once I fancied I detected the zig-zagging course which pilots usually adopt to go through the asteroid belt. If that was so we were heading for the outer planets. Jupiter, no doubt, since it was the only known source of critanium.

Finally I made up my mind to take a chance.

“Listen, all of you,” I said to my colleagues, arresting their attention from their work. “We’ve got to get action. Talking’s no use. We’re shut down here and for all we know we may be murdered or something before we ever sniff that thousand bucks. Am I right?”

They nodded sullenly.

“There’s only one way to get our rights,” I went on. “We’ve got to stop the ship! We’ll cut out the rockets and refuse to start ’em again until this woman conforms to regulations and leaves the windows free and the trap open, so we can go up for a breather every now and again. That’s the law, and we’ll enforce it. Come on, cut off the power! Close the valves!”

Naturally I had my reason for all this and stood watching in grim satisfaction while they earnestly followed out my idea. I had figured that by this time we must be pretty close to the Jovian gravity field, and therefore probably quite close to whatever secret moves Valcine Drew was proposing to make. And perhaps I could escape from down here while the confusion was being sorted out.

It meant leaving a bunch of cutthroats to take the rap, but I felt I was justified. I had a job to do: they hadn’t. Casper and the girl couldn’t do much anyway since they were powerless without men to control the rockets.

I stood watching intently as at length all sources of power were cut out and the ship continued to cruise on smoothly of its own momentum. Then came Casper’s roaring voice from the control room above.

“What the devil’s wrong with you scum down there? Use your forward tubes! What do you want us to do? Crash?”

We maintained a stony silence at that. Sure enough Casper’s heavy feet pounded over our heads along the steel corridor. The trap rattled and clanged as it was opened. He came hurrying down with a raygun in his hand. I took good care to edge my way behind him to the ladder.

“Well, what’s the idea?” he roared, glaring round. “Which of you is responsible for this? Get the hell to work!”

Still nobody answered him, so he strode down among the men and struck out savagely with the butt of his gun. Instantly he became the focus for a concerted rush. I seized the chance to steal silently up the ladder, making no sound in my rubber shoes.

In a moment I had gained the narrow corridor above. Just in time I pressed myself into the recessed doorway of a storage room as Valcine Drew appeared from the control room, obviously bent on discovering for herself what was wrong. She hurried past me, never noticing, and began to descend into the rocket hold. I could hear the noise of a rising altercation, and above it all the roaring voice of Casper, the thud of fist on bone.

Quickly I looked around me. My next job was to find concealment and yet be able to watch what happened. Carefully I edged my way down the corridor to the control room. It was empty, of course, and woefully bare of any chance of concealment. Then I glanced above me—

The very thing! Up there in the roof was the air vent trap leading into the storage containers of the circular ceiling—a kind of loft. Fine! I leaped up to the girders, swung on them quickly, and eased my way through the vent trap into the wide space beyond. Gently I lowered the trap down again and lay full length, peering through its holes. Here indeed was perfect concealment.

From this position I could also see through the broad outlook window near the switchboard. My guess that we were near Jupiter had been right. The giant planet was filling all space outside—banded, clouded, mysterious, his Great Red Spot about the only clear thing on his surface, and, as most of us pilots and spacemen well knew, the only habitable part of his surface.

Then there were his moons, all of them but briefly explored because of their inimical conditions. Frozen chunks of rock, most of them, some with vague pretensions to solidified air; others entirely without. Of the possibly habitable ones Ganymede came about the nearest. Bleak, inhospitable satellites circling round their equally unattractive primary. Right here indeed was a region where few ever ventured. Certainly the ordinary space runs never came this far; and the special ships for the critanium deposits only twice a year.

II

I LOOKED away from the window view suddenly as there were sounds beneath me. Casper and the girl came into the control room.

“Damned mutinous lot of scum,” Casper breathed savagely, jabbing his gun back in his belt. He moved the controls and since the ship reacted instantly, I presumed he’d enforced order below.

“We’ve a mutinous bunch to hold down, Valcine,” he said at length. “But I’ll do it if I break them one by one!”

I lay watching in some surprise. This struck me as a queer way for a first-mate to address the commander of the vessel. It was an even bigger surprise to see the girl’s face relax for a moment into a semblance of sympathy.

“I suppose we can’t really blame them,” she said slowly. “After all, pinned down there in that heat, all shields drawn tight—”

“Stop getting so damned sloppy!” Casper interrupted, and slipping the robot control in position for a moment he went over to a water-faucet. “Here,” he said, handing her a glass of water. “Don’t forget your medicine. Time for it.”

Intently I watched. From her belt the girl took a glass phial and shook a tablet from it into the water. She said briefly, “Don't forget to make me up some more tablets. This is the last of this supply.”

“I won’t forget,” Casper growled, and watched her drink off the draft steadily.

“That’s better,” she said, straightening up. “All right, let’s get busy.”

He nodded and I noticed there was a malignant grin on his face as he turned to the switchboard. I noticed too that Valcine had lost again that temporary look of compassion for the men below and ,was now standing grim and erect before the outlook port, studying the

From my position I saw the vessel was sweeping round to one of the moons of Jupiter. For a moment I had difficulty in placing it since most of them look alike. Then Casper cleared things up for me.

“More I see of this frozen hell of Ganymede the less I like it. But we picked a swell spot, Valcine. No guys in their right senses ever start prodding around places like this. I guess the only habitable spot in this whole gosh-awful region is the Great Red Spot up there.”

The girl nodded silently, still gazing outside. I shifted my eyes from her to the window again as Ganymede loomed up in its entirety. Cold, ruthlessly desolate little world; hardly any air; puckered into rumples and folds of rock.

Mountains seemed to be everywhere, riven asunder by bleak gorges and deadly chasms. Slowly, very slowly, this maw reached up to catch the ship as Casper lowered it gently on its under jets. We came to rest at last in the depths of a valley, smeared with the mounds of frozen, congealed air. Down here all was dark, Jove himself hidden by the mountain ranges, the only illumination coming from the icy stars.

Silent, I lay watching, wondering what was coming next. Valcine Drew and Casper seemed to be waiting for something; and after a while I saw that Casper was steadily depressing a button on the switchboard. Outside, in response, was the winking of a powerful searchlight. A signal of sorts.

Then I beheld the answer to it. Lights were coming bobbing along the valley, for all the world like miners with headlamps heading for the pit. Nearer they came, each bearing on his space suited shoulders a heavy packing case of some kind. My mind flashed instantly to illegal critanium, then I realized this could not be since it is radioactive and demands immensely heavy triple-lead containers, far heavier than a man can lift even on Ganymede’s light-gravity surface.

“Open the airlocks,” Valcine Drew said suddenly.

The valves opened one by one so no vital air escaped the control room. The first man entered, dumped his case down, then unloosed his space suit. He was not familiar to me, but from his hard bitten face and tattered uniform I placed him instantly as an ex-pilot of the space-ways, obviously fired for some misdemeanor or other. He stood looking at the girl sullenly.

“There’s a dozen of ’em this time,” he announced. “It’s worth ten thousand dollars to you.”

“You’ll get five thousand and no more,” she retorted, gazing at him. “Fetch them in—the rest of them.”

The man hesitated, burst out suddenly, “Look here, Angel, what in hell do you think me and my buddies are? Why do you think we rot out our bones in this dismal hell? Just for you to cut our prices in half? Like hell! We’ve been stuck here for a year now, hunting up Ganymedians.”

“And getting paid for it,” the girl interrupted him coldly. “If anything you’re overpaid, the whole lot of you. What more do you want?” she proceeded angrily. “I saw to it you had a comfortable base camp, food for two years, ample air—everything you need. All you have to do is hunt and collect money. In a few more trips you’ll be worth a fortune. You’ll stick it and like it! Don’t forget you can’t please yourselves, either. One word from me and the whole twelve of you are finished. There’s a nice cosy lethal chamber waiting for all of you back on Earth. This is the only, place in God’s universe where you’re safe, and you know it!”

The man was silent, biting his lip.

“Bring the rest in,” she added briefly.

HE turned and signaled into the airlock pressure room hidden from my view. One by one the spacesuited men came in, each carrying a crate. The whole dozen were finally dumped. Then Valcine Drew went to the nearest one and snapped open the side. In the interior was something I had hardly expected to see—a small humanlike creature with a big head and slender green body. The eyes were like those of a cat; the face ridiculously small and screwed up into an expression of obvious fright.

“Queer looking devils these Ganymedians,” Casper grunted, standing looking at the creature. “Queer or otherwise we’ve plenty of use for ’em, eh? Come on you—out!” and he kicked out his heavy boot, sent the little creature sprawling out of the confinement of the crate onto the floor.

“Always remind me of animated lozenges,” he grinned. “Kick your foot right through ’em if you wanted to.”

He raised his foot to kick again, purely for his own brutal amusement—but the girl stopped him.

“Give them their money,” she snapped; and turning to them, “You can have the crates back when we’re through. Make it in six hours.”

Casper went over to the cashbox and handed over the money, bundled the men roughly from the control room and slammed the airlocks after them. Through the window he watched their lamps go bobbing away into the distance.

To me all this had a definite interest. I wondered what the devil the idea was of Ganymede; even more the purpose of the poor inhabitants of this inhospitable little moon. Frail, brittle looking beings, obviously attuned to temperatures far below zero and an air too thin to ever support an Earthly form of life.

Even now the one Casper had kicked onto the floor was starting to gasp painfully in the pressures of the control room. Noticing it the girl promptly lifted him in her arms and dumped him in an upright glass case in a comer of the room. She clamped down a lid, contemplated his frightened little face for a moment, then shifted a control on the switchboard.

I saw tubes inside the case start glowing with energy. Two particular prongs turned violet and projected almost, but not quite, to the top of the creature’s shiny head. What sort of black magic was she up to now I wondered.

“Listen to me,” she said steadily, holding a microphone to her mouth. “I’m giving you instructions. Since you possess no ears my words will reach you through bone vibrations—telepathically, since that is your way of communicating. Nod your head if you understand what I’m saying.”

The head nodded vigorously.

“Good,” the girl said. “Here are your instructions: In a moment or two you will be put inside a small, globular safety ship. It will be guided by radio from this vessel. You will be sent to Jupiter, to a chosen spot, and once you land you will operate three switches connected to magnetic anchors on the ship’s exterior. I should say levers, not switches, since they are too heavy to be moved by radio and need somebody like you. They will be marked A, B and C so you cannot mistake them. On landing pull them in that order. Is that clear?”

Again came the urgent nodding.

“When that is done, which will take no more than a few minutes, radio power here will withdraw your ship back. That will end your particular task and you will be released.”

There the girl finished her communication. To me, bits of the puzzle were beginning to fit into place. It was the cold inhumanity of the idea that made me shudder. For Jupiter, biggest of all the worlds, has a gravity field of such overwhelming force that only the smallest of ships and toughest of men had ever defeated that upward drag from the planet. Going down was bad enough: coming up was sheer hell and had accounted for more pilots and engineers than I cared to remember.

Here, to save herself or her unscrupulous first mate from disaster, the girl was using slave labor. Nothing else. It was cunning—vicious. I began to realize at last how she had collected such huge amounts of critanium. I began to realize too why she had such a reputation for cruelty, and above all why nobody below was permitted to observe what was going on.

At a nod from the girl Casper went over to a valve and unscrewed it. Beyond I could see a small, but quite roomy, globe spaceship of the safety-type—not unlike a bathysphere. Into this the girl lifted the Ganymedian and then shut the airlock on him. Casper closed the valve again and pulled a lever.

“Your father would have given plenty for a system as good as this, Valcine,” he muttered. “Pity he was so sentimental: it killed lots of his chances, and I could never

talk sense into him. You and me have done a lot together, eh?

“Shut up, I’m busy,” she answered tensely.

I COULD not see immediately what happened but I guessed that explosive forces had driven the globe out through a tube into space. Valcine Drew waited a moment then turned to the radio instruments, watching a visiplate intently as the globe came into view. Carefully she began to operate the remote-control apparatus, Casper watching intently over her shoulder.

Her silence irritated me for I had felt I was on the verge of learning something worthwhile. I looked at the visiplate keenly. There, twirling down toward Jupiter, a mere black speck against his swirling cloud belts, was the solitary globe. At last it vanished in the cloud-banks, but the X-ray television never once lost track of it.

Eventually I saw it land on an unthinkably desolate plateau beneath a sky of twilit dark. The landscape, so far as I could see, was studded with gray lumps rather like dirty snow. Some of them moved visibly as the globe alighted amidst them, began to draw toward it under the pull of the magnetic anchors.

“It’s a masterpiece,” Casper breathed. “A virgin field of critanium. We got it by accident. Rather queer to think of those suckers from Earth digging for the stuff twice a year and we know the exact spot where it lies around loose. I tell you, Valcine, you and me have got about the best brains in the System.”

She didn’t answer. Her whole attention was on the controls. Finally she snapped a switch and sparks flared from the globe. It began to rise again, a whole mass of gray lumps clinging to it like barnacles to a ship. Gradually it began to rise back toward Ganymede, became larger on the screen.

Casper moved over to the outlook port and began to give directions as he watched the sky. Then when he bundled on a space-suit and went outside I guessed the globe had arrived back again. The girl operated switches on the control board and there came a rumbling thud from the firing tube. Evidently the globe had been drawn back into place by magnetism ready for the next trip.

Then there were other sounds from a remoter part of the ship. Valcine Drew waited impatiently; until at length Casper returned holding the Ganymedian by one arm. He tossed down the limply dangling body as though it were a rag doll and then commenced to take off his space suit.

“He’s dead,” he shrugged, seeing the girl’s glance. “Died, the same as they all do under the strain of leaving that hell-fired world. Well, it was worth it. He cleaned up about a million dollars’ worth of mineral that time. I’ve put it in the safety locker.”

The girl nodded composedly. “Ship okay for the next trip?”

“All set and ready.”

I’d heard of a few cold blooded rackets in my time as special agent but this had them all licked. Suddenly I thought of my micro-camera. Carefully I eased it into focusing position as the girl fired her ray pistol at the dead Ganymedian. I caught her in the very act of destroying him while Casper looked on. And I did something else too. I slipped in trying to get a better vantage point for a second photograph.

INSTANTLY two pairs of eyes stared up at the ventilator. I put my camera away promptly, waited. Just for a moment I saw real fear leap into Valcine Drew’s lovely face, then it froze again into bleak hate. A gun flashed in her hand. Almost as quickly Casper yanked one out too. He reached up with a long rod and slammed up the hatchway, stared into my face.

“You!” A start shook him. “What in hell do you think you’re doing there? Come down, damn you!” he roared.

Slowly I obeyed, dropped to the floor. The girl got up grimly from the control board, her green eyes blazing at me with unholy fury.

“How did you get up there?” Her voice was low, deadly.

“I climbed. I engineered trouble below, then while you and Casper here quelled it I did a bit of muscling up. Simple, eh?”

“Don’t try and be funny with me!” she spat back. “I’ve had my suspicions of you from the very first. In the confusion down in the hold I never noticed your absence.”

“I counted on that,” I murmured.

“You’re no ordinary rocket hand,” she went on slowly. “Just who are you?”

“Just an adventurer,” I smiled, and for that smile I was rewarded with a stinging slap in the face from the palm of her free left hand. I kept my grin as it was and that seemed to infuriate her even more.

“You’ve seen everything!” she panted. “You know—”

“I know you are slave trading through the aid of a bunch of wanted murderers,” I nodded. “I know too you are deliberately killing Ganymedians to gain critanium mineral and save your own skin and Casper’s here. I know you’re building up a fortune through methods pretty similar to those adopted by a one time Simon Legree. But one day, Valcine Drew, the law is going to catch up with you.”

“Only if you talk,” she said coldly. “I can stop that! If I choose I could have your tongue torn out so you couldn’t speak; your hands amputated so you couldn’t write. I did that once to a man who thought he could cross me.”

“Perhaps that was where you got the name of the ‘Granite Angel’?” I asked quietly.

Her only immediate response was a look of such icy fury that I knew she was quite capable of carrying put her threat. Then all of a sudden she turned aside and drummed impatiently on the control bench.

“All right,” she said slowly, thinking; “since you are so anxious to poke your nose into my affairs you might as well go the whole hog. You saw what happened to him?” She gestured in contempt to the Ganymedian.

“Well?” I asked.

“You can die being of service to me: that’s fitting. You’ll get into that safety globe and go to Jove, operate the three levers and bring back the next load of critanium.”

“What makes you think I will? You’re not dealing with a Ganymedian now, Angel. I’m an Earthman.”

“If you don’t,” she stated, coming back to me, “I’ll not withdraw the globe from Jupiter until you’ve died out there, alone, unable to move. I’ll throw a negative power over the driving controls which will lock them. I’ll destroy you. See?”

“Are you doing this because you’re afraid to kill me outright with that popgun of yours?” I asked dryly.

Her eyes flamed again. “I’m not afraid of anything! But I happen to have a crew to bring back to Earth. One short would raise an inquiry, especially if that one was found to have flame gun wounds as the cause of death. If, however, you died from pressure and spacestrain—not uncommon in space and unavoidable when leaving Jupiter—I’d have a legitimate reason for your demise. I like to play safe with the law.”

I daresay I could have played my cards well enough to make her change her view, only I didn’t. As a matter of fact another idea had formed in my mind, and it was well worth putting to the test. I noticed she looked surprised when I gave a slow nod.

“You win, Angel,” I said quietly. “Though I’d remind you I’m none too sure Jupiter will kill me. I’m no brittle man of Ganymede, remember, I’m two hundred and twenty pounds of Earthman.”

“If Jupiter doesn’t oblige, I will—and take the consequences,” she retorted. “Now get into that safety-globe.”

Shrugging, I moved to the valve and unscrewed it, clambered into the globe beyond and sank into the cushioned seat at the controls.

III

SUDDENLY the valve slammed shut again. Radio control also closed the airlock. I sat back and waited. All of a sudden I was seized with the most ghastly sinking sensation as the globe went hurtling outwards from the tube, flinging me tight back in my seat. Staring through the port I saw I was spiraling high over the rocky surface of Ganymede.

The view changed as I seemed to turn a somersault and found Jupiter suddenly below me with his heaping cloudbanks. The radio remote control was in full sway now, guiding the globe unerringly on the same course as before. In these few minutes of trip I had the chance to study the radio equipment, satisfied myself that a few brief conversions could make it suitable for ordinary short-wave transmission. That was what I wanted, later.

Again I turned my attention to the outlook port. In all directions, once I struck the cloud belts, there was just fog and nothing more—fog blown into a million wraiths and shapes by the eternal winds which roar over Jove’s surface; ammonia winds, blasted by hurricanes of between four and five hundred miles an hour in velocity.

Certainly there is no planet in the System more grim than Jupiter, a planet whereon no big space machine had ever dared to land for fear it might never again depart from the giant’s toils, or else because of the ever present hazard of meeting destruction in the furious hurricanes. Only ia small globe such as the one I was in stood any real chance by very reason of its shape.

The temperature gauge showed me what I already knew—that the external temperature was minus two hundred Fahrenheit; the air-sampler confirmed the presence of ammonia, methane, and other deadly gases in profusion.

Swiftly, still under radio control, the globe dropped until the clouds suddenly cleared and I burst on an inimical landscape. I was directly over the plateau I had seen in the X-ray telescreen—that plateau of gleaming, glassy black, frozen solid and marked here and there by the grayish lumps of the precious mineral deposits.

The lower I dropped the more I disliked the view. I cannot conceive of anything more desolate. Buffeted and battered by the atmospheric twists I went lower and lower, staring at the jagged peaks of the valley. They reared up like black towers, their basic darkness not entirely concealed by the sheen of eternal ice covering them. Half way up their Cyclopean heights the mists were swirling, blotting them out. I had only my imagination to tell me what sort of a hell must exist at the top of those monsters.

Once I landed I did more things than pull the levers to attract the critanium. I made a few tests of Jove’s surface for the the first time in my life. Atmosphere pressure and quality I already knew: the other thing I discovered was the vast pull of the gravity, so enormous I could scarcely move my jaws without experiencing pain. My hands suddenly weighed tons. I thanked God I was seated for it enabled my heart to keep a fairly steady though labored action. Certainly there was a gravity nullifier on the control board which would have put things right, only like every other switch it was locked by radio power.

Despite the physical distractions I was interested in the exterior. The ground was flint-hard, scored into innumerable rifts and furrows by the swirling hurricanes, blowing in their track monstrous surges of pebbled dust which had gouged out tracks in the ice-caked rocks. Without doubt Jupiter is no place for a vacation.

Then all of a sudden the radio controls operated again and I found myself being borne upwards with the globe once more. Hell gripped me. I gasped and choked under the strain of forcing against that titanic gravity. I realized in those moments why the weak, fragile Ganymedians had been destroyed once their job was done. Strong though I am I was doing everything in my power to protect my life. I conserved my breathing, made no movements, was gratefully content to even retain consciousness at all.

Nor did the strain weaken much for the pull of Jupiter is as strong when near Ganymede as it is when close to the surface. The only relief was when the accelerating motion ceased and I was gripped by Ganymede’s own field. Swiftly the globe spiraled back to the satellite’s desolate surface, landed finally only a few yards from the Silver Eagle.

Magnets got to work and pulled it back into the tube. I don’t think I saw two faces ever look so surprised as Casper and the girl’s as I stepped forth unharmed through the valve into the control room.

VALCINE DREW studied me for a moment, then she said briefly to Casper, “Go and see the minerals are fixed.” She waited until he was gone in his space suit then advanced toward me slowly, playing with her gun.

“So the big fellow is tough,” she murmured.

“Can’t say I didn’t warn you.” I shrugged.

“Pity it failed,” she said bitterly. “I’ll have to use the other way after all.”

“Before you do,” I interrupted her, as she leveled her gun, “there is something you ought to know. You Could never have known it if you hadn’t sent me to Jupiter as you did. You see, you’re just wasting your time collecting critanium.”

“Oh, I am! I’m quite satisfied,” she answered curtly.

“But you wouldn’t be if you’d seen what I’ve seen,” I insisted. “Down in that Jovian valley are whole seams of tranite-x! You can’t see it in that teleplate of yours because it’s below surface, but it’s there. I’ve seen it. I don’t suppose I have to add that tranite-x is worth three times as much as the stuff you keep collecting?”

Her gun lowered as she stared at me. Then Casper came back and took off his helmet. She turned to him quickly.

“You ever hear of tranite-x?”

“That’s all I have done—hear of it,” he grunted. “Frozen mineral deposit used for medical services. What about it?”

“There are whole seams of it waiting to be frisked up on Jove,” I answered him. “Just below the surface ice. And that,” I finished, looking back at the girl, “means real money.”

They were silent for a moment, then Casper looked at me in ugly suspicion.

“What’s the idea, feller? You trying to buy your liberty or something?”

I eyed him steadily. “I’m suggesting we forget our differences and get the stuff while we can. Two crates of that will make all your critanium sales look like pocket money. If you’re willing, Angel, I’ll take you with me and show you the exact spot. We can soon decide on the disposal method.”

She hesitated for a long moment.

“Afraid?” I asked cynically; and that made her flush.

“Of course I’m not afraid! I’m just thinking that it might be dangerous to lower the Eagle to Jove. We might never get away again.”

“We wouldn’t,” I confirmed grimly. “Our only chance is to use the globe. There’s room enough for the pair of us, anyway.”

“All right,” she said slowly. “We can’t afford to pass up a chance of getting tranite-x. I’ll get some samples first and bring them back for examination. If it’s the real thing we’ll have the Ganymedians mine all they can.”

“Better put some instruments in the ship—electric cutters and so forth,” I advised. “That ice is going to take a lot of smashing open.”

She nodded and motioned Casper. Still eyeing me with some doubt he put the necessary tackle into the globe, then stood aside. I clambered through the airlock into the spare seat next the control board, and the girl followed me a moment later. Casper slammed the airlock with a viciousness that clearly expressed his suspicions were deep.

I smiled grimly to myself and eyed the girl as she detached the radio remote control equipment and shifted the power levers. Casper released the power which gave us the initial send off from the tube; immediately the girl had the globe under control and we were dropping toward the storm-swept surface of Jupiter.

I sat in dead silence, but I was doing plenty of thinking. Finally my gaze dropped to the flamegun in the holster at her waist. Abruptly, before she had the least chance to grasp my intention, I’d whipped the gun free and leveled it straight at her.

She glared at me tigerishly with those green eyes of hers, but she didn’t take her hands off the Controls. She dared not.

“What’s the idea?” she demanded savagely.

“Just to make sure I have the initiative,” I smiled. “Keep on driving and you’ll be okay. Two people can play with a gun, Angel, and I’m not exactly an amateur either. Keep your hands on those switches!” I snapped, as for a moment she released them.

Her face set she looked through the port upon the swirling scum of Jove below. I don’t think I ever saw such bleak fury on a woman’s face before. It was more than anger at being tricked; it was a sheer baleful malice out of all proportion with the situation. And suddenly it must have mastered her, for her hands left the controls again.

Violently she swung in her seat and dived for my face. Just in time I jerked my head back but even at that her long, sharp nails dug savagely into my cheek. I felt the trickle of warm blood.

“You think you can do this to me?” Her voice was a positive screech as she leapt up and battered away at my head with her fists. “You clumsy great fool! You can’t—”

“The switches!” I reminded her hoarsely. “We’re falling!”

SHE was too blind with fury to notice it so I leaned across to them. Seizing her chance she picked up a spanner and brought it down with stinging force across my wrists. My hands went numb. Controlling the globe was hopeless. Helplessly I fell back in my seat, the gun dropping from my unfeeling hand. Then it was leveled at me. I stared into the girl’s cruel face as she tossed the tumbled hair out of her eyes.

“Get out of that chair, you no account space tramp!”

I moved slowly.

“Quickly!” she yelled, suddenly directing a startled glance through the window. “We’re falling!”

She dived to hurry me out of the chair and I saw her hand slide up to the gun button. In self preservation I did the only thing possible—delivered a right uppercut which hit her straight under the jaw. She collapsed her length on the metal floor.

Right then I’d no time to notice her. Frantically I worked on the Controls, but I was unfamiliar with them. In any case we had dropped into the full tug of Jupiter’s field and were whizzing downwards with diabolical speed through dense cloudbanks.

I stared out into the pall in horror.

Then we landed. The shock was terrific. I was pitched right out of the chair and landed against the padded wall. From outside came the crash of rending ice; then the globe started to roll over and over like a fast traveling snowball, came to halt finally amidst the rasp and crackle of crumbling ice shards. Somehow, dazed and bumped though I was, I managed to retain my senses.

Carefully I moved again, but the iron weights of Jupiter had sway once more. With superhuman effort I crawled to the port and stared out. All was unnaturally dark, for Jupiter has a surface twilight glow. I fingered the switches until I found the one to operate the external searchlight.

The blaze showed me we were not on the surface of the planet at all but in some kind of glassy cavern, its walls made up of sheer, black ice. For a long time I puzzled over the situation, then heard Val-cine Drew moan slightly. Immediately I returned to her and with considerable difficulty hauled her into a chair. Her weight was stupendous.

Slowly she came back to consciousness, fingering her jaw. Then as remembrance flashed back into her brain her green eyes blazed malevolently and she reached out for the gun on the floor. I was a shade quicker however and slipped it in my trousers’ belt.

“You won’t need it,” I told her briefly. “In fact neither of us will. Unless I miss my guess we’re going to be lucky if we either of us get out of this alive.”

That got her on her feet, with a strain that brought anguish into her lovely fade. She stumbled to the control board and closed a switch. Immediately the weights fell from us as Earthnorm was established in the floor. Then she went over to the port and stared outside with me. Finally her hate-filled gaze turned to me.

“This is your doing, you clumsy idiot! We must have crashed through the surface ice into an underground hole or something.”

She turned to the radio and switched it on. Then as I leaned over and prevented her seizing the microphone she stared at me fixedly.

“If you’re going to send for help from Casper, or try and get him to remote control the ship out of this mess, you’ve another think coming, Angel!”

“Don’t be an idiot! We can’t just wait here and die!”

“If there’s any way out we’ll find it for ourselves,” I said grimly. “Get away from that instrument. Go on!” I roared, as she hesitated.

I think it was her surprise at my action more than anything else that made her obey. Roughly I elbowed her aside and switched on the instruments for myself. My earlier plan to convert the radio-apparatus was unnecessary now since she’d done it for me.

“Calling Space Patrol,” I intoned into the microphone, and watched the girl out of the corner of my eye. “Calling Space Patrol...”

Her expression changed, and the moment it did so she dived for me furiously, made to grab the microphone and smash it. I struck her over the wrist with it. She fell back, holding her hand painfully.

“I owed you that one,” I said dryly, tugging out the gun and leveling it at her. “Take it easy—Hallo there! Space Patrol? Special agent Stanley speaking. Pick up a pirate space machine by the name of Silver Eagle and hold the crew and first mate Casper for full inquiry. The charge is illegal ore trading. The ship is located on Ganymede, north position. You will hold it there until further orders from me.”

SUDDENLY, my attention diverted from her for a moment, Valcine Drew acted. She lifted a heavy stool and whirled it with devastating force. It Crashed into the microphone and shattered it, drove a dent through the control panel. Instantly of course, the apparatus went dead.

“A space cop, eh?” she shouted hoarsely. “I might have known it! Well, you might get Casper but you’ll not get me! A space cop!” she went on savagely. “You’re worse than we are! You were willing to do a deal in tranite-x, and now it’s failed you are trying to get me, Casper, and my critanium mineral. You cheap, dirty double crosser!”

“Finished?” I asked impassively.

“Not yet! You’re nothing but a—”

“There is no tranite-x,” I stated quietly; then as her green eyes blazed in furious amazement I went on, “That was a simple gag to get you away from the Eagle. I wasn’t fool enough to think I could capture you and Casper single handed when you had the radio and all the advantages. The only way was to divide your forces, so to speak. Casper will be nabbed by the S.P., just as I’d planned, but my original intention to fly you in this globe to the S.P. headquarters in the Asteroid Belt will have to be altered. So far as you are concerned the plan’s slipped up. But believe me, Angel, your racket’s busted wide open from now on. Especially so with the evidence I’ve got with a micro-camera, providing I ever get away to use it. Even without it, though, your mining days are over.”

She folded her arms and smiled cynically. “And what does the copper do now?”

“Nothing,” I shrugged. “Thanks to what you’ve done to the radio we’re stuck. I can’t tell the Space Patrol to come for us, as I’d intended a moment ago. Anyway I doubt if their big machine could risk the gravity and hurricanes. So our only course is to find the way out for ourselves.”

“And if we do, you hand me over? Count me out!”

I got up, eyed her grimly. “Listen, Angel, I’m not asking for death even if you are. There’s got to be some way out, and I’m going to find it.”

“All right; I’m not stopping you. But if we get out it means death to me, so why should I help?”

“Only because death here means slow suffocation,” I said quietly. “But maybe you prefer it that way?”

She was silent, dropping her gaze. Then as though suddenly thinking of something she fingered inside the pouches on the belt she wore and pulled out a phial—that same phial I had seen her use aboard the Eagle. She took the cork out of it, then stared at its emptiness dumbly. A curious expression was on her face as she put the phial back.

“Perhaps you’re right,” she said abruptly. “I’ve got to get away from here—I’ve got to. If I don’t, it means far more than death for me.”

IV

I PUZZLED over her remark for a moment.

She seemed on the verge of explaining herself; then suddenly changed her mind.

“We’ll look around outside,” she said, and hauled two space suits to view. We were inside them in a few seconds, then armed with cutters and flashlamps we scrambled through the airlock.

We were in an ice cavern all right, virtually buried. Looking around, we could see clearly what had happened. The ship had smashed through a mass of surface ice into a depression in the ground, bringing tons of ice blocks down on top of it. Inside here, where the ship was buried, was the pocket in the ice with heaven knew how much thickness of ice above us. We were inside a natural bubble with unguess-ably thick walls. To strike upward was far too dangerous: we might precipitate an avalanche.

I linked up our helmet phones and said, “We might stand a chance at the end of the pocket there,” and I nodded to where the hollow came to an end. “If that is where the bubble ends we can work our way upwards at an angle; that should prevent any chance of a collapse.”

She nodded inside her helmet and, nailed down by the huge gravity and our studded boots skidding on the ice, we struggled forward, finally reached the solid, glittering wall which barred our one possible avenue to escape.

We went to work with our vibrator gauges first, devices which told us by etheric recoil waves exactly how thick was the barrier in front of us. It was fifteen feet, as compared to forty and fifty feet in other directions.

“Well?” the girl asked finally, looking at me.

“We drive through,” I said. “Let’s get started.”

I trailed the extension cables of our cutters back to the ship and connected them to the power plant, then each of us with a cutter apiece we set to work on the wall, standing our ground amidst the bombardment of flying ice fragments and solidified mineral deposits. It was dangerous work for the stuff was as sharp as glass. One direct impact on our space suits might very easily have made a fatal tear. However, fortune was with us.

But it was slow, grueling work in that crushing gravity. And at the end of an hour our spacesuit air tanks were running low: we had consumed a surprising amount of oxygen with our exertions and strain, and all we had to show for it was a penetration of two feet and a width of perhaps ten, just enough for the globe to pass through.

Wearied, we went back to the ship and relaxed gratefully in the Earth-norm gravity. Once I’d locked the door, I switched on the air supply to the full for a while, but a quick glance at the gauge showed me we had to husband every scrap of our supply.

“Any rations aboard?” I asked Valcine anxiously.

She nodded her blonde head tiredly toward a cupboard. In it I found a plentiful supply of canned concentrates. Far more food indeed than we could ever use with our air supply so low. In silence I put out a meal.

“Pull up,” I said briefly, and Valcine drew a chair over and sat down, to moodily regard the meal. I ate in silence for a long time before I noticed she wasn’t touching anything. All she did was take a drink then relapse into moody quiet again.

As on that other occasion on the Eagle she had at the moment lost her look of frozen viciousness and instead looked distressed, human. I was trying to figure it out to myself when she glanced at me sharply as though divining my thoughts.

“How long do you think it’ll take us to get free?” she asked.

I shrugged. “Five more shifts, I guess—if we’re lucky. It depends if the air supply will hold out that long.”

At that she unbuckled the pouched belt from about her waist and began a meticulous search of its various pockets. I watched in puzzled interest. She tipped out a variety of feminine trifles onto the table—then at last with almost a yelp of delight she pounced upon a small round tablet and flaked away the dust which was adhering to it.

Her whole manner had changed miraculously. Gone utterly was her tiredness. Quickly she hurried to the water faucet and filled up a glass, but before she could drop the tablet into the water I had grabbed it from her outstretched palm. I had remembered that other tablet back on the ship.

“What is this stuff?” I asked her curtly.

“Give it to me, please!” Her voice wasn’t cold and commanding: no, it was desperately entreating. She put the glass down and stared at me urgently.

“Why?” I insisted. “What does a girl like you in the prime of health need with tablets anyway?”

“Prime of health!” She laughed hollowly. “If you only knew how funny that is!”

I stared at her. “But I don’t understand.”

“If you must know, I have space fever,” she interrupted. “I’ve had it for a year now. You know what it does unless tablets of calrax are taken regularly every five hours. It seeps into your bones, slowly destroys the nerves, brings horrible agonizing death. Only by these tablets can I keep myself in anything like normal health. Give it to me! All this is Casper’s fault. I came off on this trip without getting a fresh supply from him. I’m lucky to find this odd one.”

I LOOKED at her fixedly, still holding the tablet. I have seen space fever in all its phases, and I know it produces certain unmistakable signs even when the sufferer uses calrax to antidote it. For instance, it leaves the whites of the eyes muddy and yellow; it contracts the pupils; it makes the hands knotted as though with acute arthritis. Yet Valcine Drew had none of these symptoms.

“Who told you you have space fever?” I demanded.

“Casper of course. I got it on one of our trips and he made up these tablets for me—has done ever since.... Oh please give me that tablet!” she nearly screamed. “I feel ill! I’ve got to have it!”

“In a moment,” I said, and hurrying over to the microscope I put the tablet on the slide, studied it carefully. She did not interfere but watched with itching impatience. I saw plenty through the lenses which startled me.

“Valcine,” I said slowly, looking up, “there’s a lot about you that I’m only just beginning to understand. For instance, your harshness, your disregard of all law, your stubborn courage. To speak plainly, you’ve poisoned yourself with these tablets until you couldn’t help but be that way! Or rather Casper has seen to it that you have poisoned yourself!”

“What do you mean.” She stared at me bewilderedly.

“I mean that this pill is not calrax! I know the stuff backwards. It’s olvis-root powder made into a pill and bound with some sort of glucose. Do I have to tell you what even a few grains of olvis-root will do?”

The color drained still more from her pale face. From the utter horror in her eyes I could see she knew as well as I that olvis-root is deadly poison, obtainable from Venus’ toxic lands.

“It—it deadens the nerves, alters the impulses, destroys fear, operates on every gland secretion,” she breathed, half to herself. “Yes, yes, I know what it does. God, now I begin to see! What I contracted was nothing more than a touch of space radiation perhaps; it’s common enough. That devil Casper started to feed me olvis-root poison tablets in quantity enough to change my entire nature as long as the effect lasted. Yes—that’s it! Now I know the reason why he never missed telling me the times for my pills. I thought it was concern for my welfare—The beast! The filthy, dirty beast!”

She sat down heavily, staring at me. Then she went on,

“Before I had space fever, or whatever it was, I used to work with my father in legitimate ore mining. Casper wanted us to do it illegally and make a fortune. I think, though I can’t prove it, that he killed dad in order to put his devilish plans into effect. When dad died, I was left alone in space with Casper. He tried to force me to agree to piracy, and I wouldn’t. It was against all my natural principles.

“Then I was taken ill, and I see now that it was since then that I have been a changed woman. Cruelty suddenly appealed to me; sadism was as natural as breathing. I was proud of my name of ‘The Granite Angel.’ So Casper deliberately destroyed my real nature to make me a willing ally—to make me the scapegoat for everything when justice caught up.”

Suddenly she dropped her flaxen head to her restless hands. Just as quickly she got up and started pacing agitatedly.

“Don’t you see what he’s done to me? I cannot live now without the drug! Every time I lost my sense of courage and harshness he gave me a tablet, and in this one tablet here is my one chance of preserving my life until I can get more. Without them the reaction is deadly. Insufferable weariness; a slow decline into death. Anybody knows that olvis-root victims die swiftly if the supply is stopped.”

She stopped, staring at me. I wish I could fully describe the wild loveliness of her now she was temporarily herself. I freely admit I wanted nothing more than to take her in my arms and swear the most impossible resolutions in order to save her. But being a trained realist I tried instead to find a way round the problem.

“Whatever happens,” I said quietly, “you are not going back to your old role. I’d sooner see you dead than that. If I read your true character aright you’d sooner be dead than....”

SHE stood facing me, hands clenched at her sides. Abruptly I decided the issue by dropping the pill on the floor and grinding it under my heel. She watched my action dumbly. Quietly I went to the medicine chest and shook restorative powder into the water she’d drawn.

She drank it off, then sat down again wearily.

“Listen, Valcine,” I said seriously, taking her limp hand, “if we once get out of this jam there are hospitals on Earth fully equipped to deal with your problem. You can be cured, and though in honor bound I shall be forced to hand you over to the law, I have no doubt of the verdict. A victim of olvis-root poisoning isn’t responsible to anybody or anything. It is Casper—and he alone—who’ll take the rap. Understand?”

“I’m answerable to my conscience,” she said bitterly. “The unspeakable things I have done. Nothing can eradicate the penalty due me for that.” She stopped and winced with transient pain, then said, “I—I must rest awhile.”

With that she coiled herself up on the single bunk by the wall and was soon asleep. Finally, after a long study of her beautiful features in repose I cursed and damned Casper until I could curse no more. Then I lowered the air pressure and lay down on the floor to doze.

I awakened again to find Valcine shaking me.

“We must get busy again,” she said urgently. “The air is getting so much weaker!”

I nodded and scrambled up, studied her quickly. She looked wan, her eyes dead with weariness even though she had slept. We had a small meal then got into our spacesuits once more and recharged the air cylinders. This revived us a little and we set out on our task again. We kept at it until fatigue got us down again, but our cutters had done good work. I almost dared to hope that we could cut things short by a sudden forward impetus which might smash the remaining barrier and drive us right out into space.

I told this to Valcine when we got back into the ship. She turned from studying the air gauge.

“We shall have to do so,” she said seriously. “Our air will only last that long anyway. Don’t forget that in getting away from Jupiter we shall draw enormously on the air because of the strain on our lungs with the acceleration. We’ve barely enough to get away with.”

I went to her side and looked at the ominous needle. Barely enough was right.

“Of course,” I said, thinking, “there is another way. By this time the space patrol will have picked up Casper. Suppose I were to stay behind in the cavern outside here, protected by a spacesuit? I’d have the air cylinder. You could go ahead and tell the S.P. Then recharge the globe with air and come back for me. You’d have ample air to make that journey from here alone.”

“Walk right into the lion’s jaws, eh?” she asked somberly.

“Only as a means to your final escape from your beastly other self. Only as a means to absolute cure.”

She smiled faintly. “Cure? I wonder. I feel burned out. Dead. I doubt if I’d ever live long enough to reach a hospital anyway. Besides, how do you know I’d ever come back for you?”

“I just... know,” I said.

Her eyes looked into mine, reflecting something of what I was thinking. But at last she shook her head slowly.

“No—I can’t go to the S.P. and tell them to return here. I can’t even face them. I’ve my conscience to reckon with. There is a better way. You go alone and I’ll stay behind in a spacesuit. You can arrange the details for the S.P. to come and take me.”

“I won’t do it,” I said firmly.

“If you love me, Stanley—you will.”

It was the first time she had ever used what she thought was my Christian name and it made me stare at her for the moment. Then almost before I had realized it I was covering her face with kisses and telling her my real name was Curtis Stanley.

“And Val, I do love you,” I whispered.

“Then, Curt, do as I say, please! Every minute is precious. It’s the only way I can feel easy in my mind. For you to explain things away a bit about me first to the S.P. If I know you’re coming back I’ll last out, until we get to a hospital.”

Then she had turned quickly and was clambering into her space suit. Before she put on the helmet she gave a long, lingering gaze with wistful eyes. Then her helmet snapped in place and she climbed out through the airlock.

I WATCHED through the port until she was at a safe distance, then clamping the airlock I moved to the control board. Carefully, I let in the power switches. The globe started vibrating on the ice. Ahead of me was the brief tunnel with its rearing wall, into which I might easily smash to destruction. And behind was—

It was Valcine! She was running back toward the globe just as it started to move down the slope. What the devil was she doing? The flaring of the rocket exhaust might quite easily melt the ice columns and bring down tons of ice and rock upon her.

It was too late now to stop. The globe was hurtling for the barrier. I wasn’t even looking at it. I could see Valcine had stopped now and was waving.

Then in a tumult of endless thunders the thing happened. Ice, rocks, mineral ores—the whole lot crumbled in behind the fast moving globe and blotted her out of sight in chaos. At the same moment I was hurled back in my chair as I smashed right through the ice wall and went soaring away against the merciless Jovian pull, battling with the tempest.

Up and up. I hardly realized what I was doing. As I plowed through ammonia fog with laboring heart I pieced together odd bits. I remembered Valcine’s reference to her conscience. I remembered too that she had deliberately walked back into the danger area in the ice-hole—

Air enough for one—and she had wished it to be me!

Dully I stared in front of me. To the end of my days I shall remember a lone figure—an infinitely courageous figure—waving a last good-by before the obliterating thunder of an avalanche.